<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The key of knowledg opening the principles of religion, and the path of life directing the practice of true peitie design'd for the conduct of children and servants in the right way to heaven and happiness / by T. W. D. D.</title>
            <author>Willis, Thomas, 1582-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 210 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65362</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W122</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6903</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13506484</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13506484</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99817</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65362)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99817)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 480:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The key of knowledg opening the principles of religion, and the path of life directing the practice of true peitie design'd for the conduct of children and servants in the right way to heaven and happiness / by T. W. D. D.</title>
                  <author>Willis, Thomas, 1582-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 170 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Thomas Willis.  Cf. BMC and DNB.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Future life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99817:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99817:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Key of Knowledg,</hi> Opening <hi>The PRINCIPLES of RELIGION;</hi> And <hi>The Path of Life,</hi> Directing The PRACTICE of true PIETIE: Deſign'd For the Conduct of <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> in the right way to Heaven and Happineſs.</p>
            <p>By <hi>T. W.</hi> D. D.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 22.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Train up [or, <hi>Chatechize</hi>] a Child in the way he ſhould go: and when he is Old he will not depart from it.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 119.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>VVherewith ſhall a <hi>Young man</hi> cleanſe his way? By taking heed thereto according to thy VVord.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the Bible and three Crowns, at the lower end of <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers Chappel.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:99817:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99817:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <head type="sub">To all young Perſons, who deſire a happy life here; and, in the end, Eternal life in Heaven.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>REmember thy Creatour in the Daies of thy youth,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.1.</note> is the wiſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of the wiſeſt of men, <hi>Solomon.</hi> A multitude of young People neglecting this great Duty, and never ſeriouſly thinking of that God that made them, have run headlong into Hell fire. And what a wofull thing is it for any to ſpend their time in <hi>vain Pleaſures</hi> here, and then to lie roaring in <hi>intolerable pains</hi> in Hell for ever and ever! Take heed leſt this be thy ſtate, who now readeſt theſe Lines. Know, tho' thou perceiveſt it not, thou now ſtandeſt upon the very edge and brink of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity. The leaſt touch of God's
<pb facs="tcp:99817:3"/>hand may ſend thee into another world. Thou art a mortal Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. As ſure as thou liveſt, thou muſt at length die: and then what ſhall become of thy Soul to Eternity? When thy Body drops into the duſt, thy Soul which never dies, will go to Heaven or Hell, there to remain for ever and ever. And how ſoon thou may'ſt die thou knoweſt not. If thou vainly flattereſt thy ſelf with hopes of long life, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.20.</note> God may ſay to thee, <hi>Thou fool, this night thy Soul ſhall be required of thee,</hi> And then where art thou? Do'ſt thou yet know thy State? Thou waſt <hi>born in Sin, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh</hi> 9.34. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3.</note> being by Nature a Child of Wrath,</hi> and Heir of Hell. If thou art ſtill in this ſtate (as thou certainly art, unleſs thou art <hi>born again</hi>) thou ſtandeſt upon the <hi>Brink of Hell,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3.</note> and art every moment in danger of eternal Damnation. Nothing but the Patience of God, upon which thou do'ſt daily treſpaſs by every Sin thou committeſt, keeps thee out of the <hi>burning Lake,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8.</note> that
<pb facs="tcp:99817:3"/>place of torment which is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for Sinners. And tho' thou canſt eat, drink, and be merry, and when the night is come, lie down in thy Bed and ſleep ſecure, certain it is thou art all this while within an <hi>hand's-breadth</hi> of Hell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire. For what's thy Life?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.5.</note> 
               <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>thou haſt made my daies as an hand-breadth, and mine age is as nothing before thee: verily every man at his beſt ſtate is altogether vanity.</hi> And again ſaith he, <hi>the wicked ſhall be turn'd into Hell.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.17.</note> So that while thou art in the guilt of Sin, thou hangeſt by a <hi>brittle thread,</hi> a frail Life, over the burning Lake; and by every Sin thou committeſt, thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vokeſt God to cut this thread in two. How canſt thou live ſecure, when there is nothing but this poor <hi>Paper-wall</hi> of a mortal body between thy Soul and Hell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire?</p>
            <p>Now if thou art not ſtrangely ſtupid, and one whom God hath already ſealed up under <hi>hardneſs of heart</hi> to Damnation, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Acts</hi> 28, 27.</note> thou
<pb facs="tcp:99817:4"/>may'ſt plainly perceive, that thou art infinitely concern'd, with all poſſible ſpeed, to take care that <hi>thy Soul may be ſaved,</hi> that ſo, whenever it ſhall pleaſe God to take thee hence by death, thou may'ſt be for ever happy in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. How happy would'ſt thou be all the reſt of thy days, if thou had'ſt but once ſecur'd the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy Soul, and waſt but well aſſur'd thou ſhould'ſt be happy for ever?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But what ſhall I do to be ſaved? <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 16.30.</note> What muſt I do that I may go to heaven when I die? If I knew how to ſecure the ſalvation of my Soul, it ſhould be the firſt thing I would do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is this thy Enquiry and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve? Art thou in good earneſt? Then know that this <hi>little Book</hi> is very happily come into thy hand. For the very Deſign of it is to make plain the <hi>way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> to thee, and to tell thee <hi>what thou muſt know, and do to be ſaved,</hi> and give thee a plain direction for the doing of it, ſo that, if thou do'ſt not wilfully <hi>deſtroy thy ſelf,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:99817:4"/>thou may'ſt certainly be ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly happy.</p>
            <p>Know then that there are ſome things which God hath made ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be known and beleiv'd to Salvation: and ſome things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be done. <hi>The know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God and Chriſt, and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Gospel, requiring Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, Faith, and Holy life,</hi> are altogether neceſſary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Son of God, who is the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Saviour of loſt men, hath plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declar'd that he will not ſave any but upon theſe terms, And therefore tho' <hi>This is a faithfull ſaying and worthy of all acceptation,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15.</note> that Chriſt Jeſus came into the world to ſave ſinners:</hi> yet it is no leſs certain, that <hi>He ſhall at length be revealed from Heaven, with his mighty Angels, in fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Fire, to take vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not the Gospel of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1, 7, 8, 9.</note> who ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting Deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, and
<pb facs="tcp:99817:5"/>from the glory of his power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now theſe things which are ſo neceſſary to ſalvation, are here briefly comprehended in a ſhort <hi>Scripture-Catechiſm,</hi> which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I adviſe thee to get perfectly by heart. Know the <hi>Anſwers</hi> are the very words of Scripture, which is the very <hi>Word of God,</hi> on which thou may'ſt ſafely venture thy Soul. And when thou canſt readily repeat theſe words, with the mention of the places of Scripture where they are to be found, thou wilt be able <hi>to give any man that asks thee, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.</note> a Reaſon of thy</hi> Faith, <hi>or Hope,</hi> by a ready mention of that Scripture on which it is grounded.</p>
            <p>But that thy <hi>Hope may not make thee aſham'd,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5.</note> reſt not in the bare repeating of theſe words, and bearing them in thy memory, but be ſure thou knoweſt well the meaning of the things required of thee for thy Salvation, by thy own ſenſe and experience; as of Repentance and Regeneration or being born of the Spirit, faith in
<pb facs="tcp:99817:5"/>Chriſt, and Obedience to the Goſpel. Do the things, and ſo ſhalt thou beſt know the meaning of the words, for thy Souls good. To do God's will is the only way to have a ſaving knowledge of his word. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.17.</note> 
               <hi>If any man</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>will do his Will, he ſhall know my Doctrine to be of God.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 3.19.</note> Repent therefore and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted;</hi> break off thy ſins with a hearty ſorrow that thou haſt thereby offended a good God, and lead a new life: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 16.31.</note> Believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and truſt in him alone for thy Salvation. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.21.</note> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thy ſelf to him, and ſeriouſly endeavour to do all thoſe things which he requires of thee in his word and Goſpel, and <hi>thou ſhalt be ſaved, and inherit life Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What <hi>Duties</hi> God requires of thee, whether as a <hi>Child</hi> or a <hi>Servant,</hi> I have plainly ſhew'd thee from the word of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Read thy Duty oft, and never ſail to do it. This is the way to bring down God's Bleſſing upon
<pb facs="tcp:99817:6"/>thee, and to become happy in his favour.</p>
            <p>When thou comeſt to be of a competent Age (that of ſixteen years is the ordinary time) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thy ſelf for the right recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Bleſſed Sacrament of the <hi>Lord's Supper.</hi> Know that in thy <hi>Baptiſm</hi> a ſolemn <hi>Covenant</hi> was ſealed, whereby thou waſt obliged <hi>to forſake the World, the Fleſh, and the Devill, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in God, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iack.</hi> 1.74, 75.</note> and ſerve him, in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs all the days of thy life.</hi> Now know, if the Vanities and Pleaſures of this world, gratifying thy natural ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites and Inclinations, have drawn off thy mind and heart from the Remembrance, Love and Service of God, thou haſt bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken thy <hi>Baptiſmal vow.</hi> For in ſtead of forſaking the World for God, thou haſt forſaken God for the world, and thereby gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified thine own Fleſh and Satan, to the certain hazard and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance of the ſalvation of thy Soul. But in the Holy Sacrament
<pb facs="tcp:99817:6"/>of the Lord's Supper, God is pleaſed to invite thee to <hi>renew thy Covenant</hi> with Him, for thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſtatement in thy forfeited Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, and thy more firm eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in a happy ſtate of Grace and Salvation. For herein upon thy hearty Repentance, and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt Faith in Chriſt, he will ſeal un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee the free and full Pardon of all thy paſt Sins, and a Right to all the Priviledges of the Covenant of Grace, and Felicities of the Kingdom of Glory.</p>
            <p>Oh think it a happy Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, wherein thou may'ſt begin the world anew with God and be in as fair a State of Favour with him, and have as firm a Hope of Happineſs in Heaven, as if thou hadſt never ſinn'd againſt him. For <hi>the Bloud of Chriſt</hi> is exhibit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in its Virtue in that Sacrament, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.28.</note> to <hi>cleanſe thee from all Sin;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.18.</note> ſo that tho' thy Sins were as <hi>Scavlet or Crimſon,</hi> thy Soul ſhall become as <hi>white as wool, or ſnow in Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> in the ſight of God. And moreover hereby thou mayſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb facs="tcp:99817:7"/>a <hi>Communication of thoſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and comforts</hi> of the Spirit of God, which may enable thee to that chearfull obedience to his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Commands, which will fit thee for the fruition of all the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Covenant of Grace, and prepare thee for all the Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities of the Kingdome of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p>That thou may'ſt not fail of theſe ineſtimable Benefits, do not neglect this Bleſſed Ordinance; but when thou haſt an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to receive it, ſeriouſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thy ſelf for it. For this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe get by heart the <hi>Catechiſm for Communicants.</hi> And when the time of the Adminiſtration ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, withdraw thy ſelf from all Company into thy private chamber, or ſome convenient place, and there ſetting thy ſelf as in the ſight and preſence of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, ſeriouſly ſet upon the neceſſary work of <hi>Self-Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I have made very plain and caſie to thee, in that <hi>Pattern
<pb facs="tcp:99817:7"/>or example</hi> of it which I have ſet before thee. Read it only with a ſerious attention and Self-applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and thy work is done. For hereby thou may'ſt clearly diſcern thy <hi>Spiritual State,</hi> which is the great end of Self-examination. And when hereby thou diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt thy <hi>Sins and Defects,</hi> humbly and heartily bewail them before God, and earneſtly beg <hi>Mercy and Grace,</hi> ſtedfaſtly reſolving to lead a new Life, and to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God by a better obedience for the time to come. This thou may'ſt doe in the uſe of that <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and Prayer,</hi> which is here fitted for that purpoſe. Fall down on thy knees therefore, and with all the ſeriouſneſs, humility, and devotion thou canſt, make thy <hi>Confeſſion and Prayer</hi> to God; and ſo may'ſt thou with <hi>ſafety and comfort</hi> go to the Lords Table, that the <hi>Pardon</hi> of thy ſins, and the <hi>Promiſes</hi> of the Covenant may be ſeal'd up to thy Soul, in the Bloud of thy Saviour; and that all thy <hi>Defects and VVants</hi> may be
<pb facs="tcp:99817:8"/>ſupply'd from his abundant Grace; and ſo thou mayſt be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with ſtrength for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and filled with comfort and Joy in the hopes of his Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſeriouſly engag'd thy ſelf in a <hi>holy courſe of life,</hi> perſevere in it to the end. Know now, Heaven is before thee, Hell behind thee: it's wofull to <hi>draw back to Perdition;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>perſevere to the ſaving of thy Soul.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.39.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To this end be <hi>inſtant in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.12.</note> and endeavour to make a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Progreſs in Piety, <hi>to grow in knowledge and Grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18.</note> whereby thou wilt daily make a nearer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to the Kingdome of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p>Let no day paſs without Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Conſider in the morning, it was God that kept thee the laſt night; and if he do not keep thee and ſuſtain thee, thou canſt not live another day. And why ſhould he keep thee, if thou wilt not praiſe him for thy preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:99817:8"/>nor pray to him to preſerve thee? Go not out then without Prayer, leſt God be angry; and either cut off thy life from the Earth, or ſhut thee out of Heaven.</p>
            <p>At night, kneel down on thy knees to pray, before thou lieſt down on thy bed to ſleep; leſt preſuming to ſleep in the guilt of ſin, thou ſhould'ſt awake in the flames of Hell. Make thy peace with God therefore by a hearty ſorrow for the ſins of that day, with an earneſt Prayer for pardon. So mayſt thou <hi>lie down in peace, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.8.</note> and ſleep in ſafety,</hi> under God's protection. But ſtill think this night, this day may be my laſt, and ſo demean thy ſelf as if at the end thereof thou waſt to appear before God in judgment.</p>
            <p>For thy help in this holy courſe I have here furniſhed thee with certain <hi>Forms of Prayer and praiſe:</hi> do thou add <hi>Spirit and life</hi> to them by offering them up daily with a holy fervour of affection to God. The tongue may repeat the
<pb facs="tcp:99817:9"/>words, but 'tis the heart muſt make the Prayer. For that's no Prayer to God, which is not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd up with a holy motion, a pious affection of the heart and Soul of man. Pray then that thou mayſt have grace to live well, and then live as thou prayeſt, and live for ever.</p>
            <p>And that thou may'ſt ſo live here, as that thou may'ſt for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver live with God in glory, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently obſerve thoſe <hi>Rules of good life,</hi> which I have given thee out of the word of God. Read them often on the <hi>Lord's Daies,</hi> and eſpecially on thoſe daies on which thoureceiveſt the Holy-Sacrament of the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in reneweſt thy reſolution and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bligation to honour God by a <hi>Holy life.</hi> Live according to theſe Rules: carefully ſhun eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry known ſin, and neglect no known Duty, that thou may'ſt be able to ſay (with St. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>herein do I exerciſe my ſelf to have alwaies a conſcience void of off ence, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 24.16.</note> hoth toward God, and toward men.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:99817:9"/>
            <p>And that thou mayſt proceed in this path of Piety with more pleaſure, I have furniſht out a ſhort <hi>Banquet</hi> for thy Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with <hi>Holy Delight,</hi> in a brief Collection of ſome few pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Divine Poems,</hi> which may ſerve to imbelliſh the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, and delight the mind.</p>
            <p>Having thus begun, and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4.</note> endeavour to <hi>go on to Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Not to go forward ſtill in Gods way, is to go backward. <hi>The path of the juſt is as the ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning light, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.18.</note> that ſhineth more and more unto the perfect day.</hi> To this end daily read the <hi>Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> wherein God has revealed his will to man, unfolded the myſteries of Grace, and made plain before us the path to eternal Life and Glory. This is <hi>God's Book,</hi> and therefore to be read with Reverence, and preferr'd before all other Writings in the world. On the <hi>Lord's Day</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſpend ſome time in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding God's word. And when thou takeſt this Bleſſed Book in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:99817:10"/>thy hand, lift up thy heart to Heaven, and pray for the <hi>Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the Spirit,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.17, 18. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.30.</note> that thou mayſt <hi>underſtand what thou rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt</hi> Meditate on what thou haſt read and heard, and endeavour to turn it into practice, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it to thy comfort and joy in the hope of glory.</p>
            <p>And thus I have ſhew'd thee the <hi>Way to Heaven,</hi> a plain path to an eternal Paradiſe. If thou lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt thy ſoul, delay not to enter into it, and walk in it. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs there are thouſands of young people, who ſometimes reſolved to repent and lead new lives: but being loath ſo ſoon to leave off the <hi>Pleaſures of ſin,</hi> alas! they were ſurpriz'd with Death, and muſt now ſuffer eternall pains in Hell. Be warn'd; be wiſe: <hi>be good betimes, and be happy for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Aſſure thy ſelf by ſetting with ſeriouſneſs upon the <hi>Practice of true Pietie,</hi> thou ſhalt not looſe the <hi>pleaſures of life,</hi> but exchange them for purer and ſweeter. So
<pb facs="tcp:99817:10"/>much joy ſprings up in a truly pious Soul, in the ſenſe of God's Favour, and in the hopes of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that it far exceeds all the Pleaſures and Delights of this world; and the delight of well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing ſurpaſſes <hi>the pleaſures of ſin, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.25. <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.23. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.8. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.6.</note> that are but for a ſeaſon.</hi> They are <hi>Fools that make a mock and ſport of ſin:</hi> but 'tis the ſpeech of a ſerious Saint, <hi>I delight to do thy will, O my God! yea, thy Law is within my heart. The laughter of a fool</hi> (and ſuch is the Sinner, that laughs while he ſtands on the brink of Hell and Deſtruction) <hi>is but as the crackling of thorns un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der apot;</hi> 'tis but a flaſh of vain mirth, which will end in bitter pangs of long-abiding Sorrow. What reaſon has he to laugh here, that ſhall weep and mourn in Hell? But the joy of a good man is as the <hi>Day-break</hi> of eternal Bliſs: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 34.8. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>Oh taſte, and ſee then that the LORD is good and gracious.</hi> He that may freely drink pure wine, will never be perſuaded to quench his thirſt with puddle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water.
<pb facs="tcp:99817:11"/>He that purſues the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Luſt and ſin, ſeeks to quench his thirſt at a <hi>vile puddle;</hi> when in the Practice of true Piety, he might daily drink of the <hi>wine of Paradiſe.</hi> Such are thoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Comforts and Joys which ſpring up in a pious Soul, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God and Chriſt. Certainly a <hi>Holy life</hi> is the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieſt life of man on earth, and the certain way to everlaſting hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs in Heaven. Thus live then, and when thou dieſt, be happy for ever. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jude v.</hi> 24, 25.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now unto him that is able to keep thee from falling, and to preſent thee faultleſs before the preſence of his glory with exceeding joy, to the onely wiſe God our Saviour, be Glory and Majeſty, Dominion and power, both now and ever. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:99817:11"/>
            <head>The TITLES of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral TRACTS, or PARTS of this Book.</head>
            <p n="1">I. A brief Compendium of Scripture-Catechiſm, exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the firſt principles of the Oracles of God.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Scripture-Monitor, declaring the duties of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Servants.</p>
            <p n="3">III. A Catechiſm for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants, for the Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe who are to receive the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Self-Examination; ſhewing the Qualification of a worthy Communicant.</p>
            <p n="5">V. Chriſtian Devotion, in Forms of Prayer and praiſe, for Children and Servants.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:99817:12"/>
            <p n="6">VI. Chriſtian Converſation, or directions for leading a good Life.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Apples of Gold in Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of Silver; or ſome choice Pieces of Divine Poeſie, for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and Delight of young people.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:99817:12"/>
            <head>A Brief Compendium of <hi>Scripture-Catechiſm:</hi> Exhibiting <hi>The firſt PRINCIPLES of the OR ACLES of GOD</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12.</note>.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>§ 1. Of God.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>WHAT muſt you do that you may be happy for ever?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Know God, and ſerve him; 1 Chron. 28.9.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God is a Spirit, <hi>and</hi> the Father of Spirits; John 4.24. with Heb. 12.9.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But what is he for Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and Dominion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The King eternal, immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, inviſible, the onely wiſe God; 1 Tim. 1.17.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are there more Gods than One?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:99817:13"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There is but one God; 1 Cor. 8.6.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But how many Perſons are there in the Godhead?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are three; 1 Joh. 5.7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>By what names are they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt; Mat. 28.19.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are theſe three but one God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Theſe Three are one; 1 Joh. 5.7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>By what name hath this one true God manifeſted himſelf to men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the name of God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty; Exo. 6.3.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is he not as well Merciful as Mighty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The LORD is Merciful and Gracious; Pſal. 103.8.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is he for Counſel and Execution?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Great in Counſel, and Mighty in work; Jer. 32.19.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What great work hath God done?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God made the World; and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99817:13"/>all things therein; Acts 17.24.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is he then Lord of all?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He is Lord of Heaven and Earth; Acts 17.24.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And doth he govern all as King?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> His Kingdom ruleth over all; Pſal. 103.19.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is it he then that hath made us, and all men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is he that hath made us, and not we our ſelves; Pſ. 100.3.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And are we all ſuſtain'd in life by him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In him we live, and move, and have our being; Acts 17.28.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And doth he give us all we have?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He giveth to all Life, and Breath, and all things; Acts 17.25.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§ 2. <hi>Of Man.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>OF what did God at firſt form man</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The LORD God formed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99817:14"/>man of the duſt of the ground; Gen. 2.7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>In what likeneſs did he make him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God created man in his own Image; Gen. 1.27.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Wherein was man made like to God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In Knowledge, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and true Holineſs; Col. 3.10. with Eph. 4.24.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When God had thus made man, where did he put him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Into the Garden of Eden; Gen. 2.15.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And what Charge and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand did he give him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of the Tree of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Good and Evil thou ſhalt not eat; <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Did he notwithſtanding eat of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He did eat; Gen. 3.6.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Were many the worſe for this fault of one?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By one mans diſobedience many were made Sinners; Rom. 5.19.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:99817:14"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>What evil came upon all men hereby?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the offence of one judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment came upon all men to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demmation; Rom. 5. 18.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Shall all men then, being thus condemn'd, everlaſtingly pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There is no Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to them that are in Chriſt- Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; Rom. 8.1.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§ 3. <hi>Of Chriſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVHo is this Jeſus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Jeſus is the Son of God; 1 Joh. 5.5.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And was he ſent to be our Saviour?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Father ſent the Son to be the Saviour of the World; 1 Joh. 4.14.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And did he accordingly come to ſave us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt came into the world to ſave Sinners; 1 Tim. 1.15.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:99817:15"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>After what manner did he come into the world?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He took upon him the form of a ſervant, and was made in the likeneſs of men; Phil. 2.7</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is he not true God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He is the true God; 1 Joh. 5.20.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Being true God; how was he made in the likeneſs of men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Being made of a woman; Gal. 4.4.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What was this woman?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Virgin eſpouſed to a man, whoſe name was Joſeph; Luk. 1.27.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And what was the Virgin's Name?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Virgins Name was Mary; Luk. 1.27.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Being a Virgin, how came ſhe to be with child?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the Holy Ghoſt; Mat. 1.18.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And where was he Born of her?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Jeſus was born in Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lehem; Mat. 2.1.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What was this Bethlehem?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:99817:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The City of David; Luk. 2.11.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Being thus made man, what did he for mans Salvation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He humbled himſelf, and became obedient unto death, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the death of the Croſs; Phil. 2.8.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What was done to him after his death?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He was buried; 1 Cor. 15.4.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But did he not riſe again?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He roſe again the third day; 1 Cor. 15.4.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And whether did he then go?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He was received up into Heaven, and ſate on the right hand of God; Mark. 16.19.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What mean you by his ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the right hand of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God hath highly exalted him; Phil. 2.9.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What power hath he given him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All Power is given to him in Heaven and in Earth; Mat. 28.18.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is he then fully able to ſave loſt Sinners?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:99817:16"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He is able to ſave them to the uttermoſt that come to God by him; Heb. 7.25.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And is there no Salvation in any other?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Neither is there Salvation in any other; Acts 4.12.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Who ſhall be ſaved by him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He that Believeth, and is Baptized, ſhall be ſaſed: but he that Believeth not, ſhall be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; Mark 16.16.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>§ 4. <hi>Of Duties.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>IF Believing be ſo neceſſary to Salvation, tell me how we muſt come by this Faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word of God; Rom. 10.17.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What call you the word of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Holy Scriptures, which are able to make <hi>me</hi> wiſe to Salvation; 2 Tim. 3.15.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is Baptiſm ordinarily neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Salvation?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:99817:16"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Except a man be born of Water, and the Spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God; Joh. 3.5.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What mean you by being born of water and the Spirit?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The waſhing of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and the renewing of the Holy ghoſt; Tit. 2.5.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Does the promiſe of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt, which is the ground of Baptiſm, belong to us that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve only, or to our children al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The promiſe is to you, and to your children; Acts 2.39.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>In whoſe name is baptiſm to be adminiſtred?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt; Mat. 28.19.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How ſhould we walk who have been baptized?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We ſhould walk in new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of life; Rom 6.4.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How ſhould we walk in new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Denying ungodlineſs and worldly Luſts, we ſhould live
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99817:17"/>ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world; Tit. 2.12.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>That we may ſo live here then, as that we may enter into life eternal in the end, what muſt we do?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Keep the Commandments; Mat. 19.17.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhich is the first and great Commandment of the Law?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy <hi>God</hi> with all thy heart, and with all thy Soul, and with all thy mind; Mat. 22.37.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhich is the ſecond that is like to it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt love thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as thy ſelf; Mat. 22.39.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But what need is there of our Obedience? Did not Chriſt by his ſufferings become the Saviour of all Sinners?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He became the Author of eternal Salvation to all them that obey him; Heb. 5.9.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat hath he in his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel ſaid to us, to engage our Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience unto him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> If ye love me, keep my
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99817:17"/>Commandments; Joh. 14, 15.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat ſpecial Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath he given us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To love one another; 1 Joh. 3.23.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And what charge hath he given us concerning our enemies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Love your Enemies, do good to them that hate you, Luk. 6.27.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What muſt he do that will become Chriſts Diſciple indeed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Deny himſelf, and take up his Croſs daily, and follow <hi>Him;</hi> Luk. 9.23.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And what hath he ſaid to encourage us to his Service?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Where I am, there ſhall alſo my Servant be: and if any man ſerve me, him will my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther honour; Joh. 12.26.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Beſides Baptiſm for our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion into the Church, what are we enjoyn'd for our holding Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To eat the Lord's Supper; 1 Cor. 11.20.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat charge hath Chriſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us concerning this?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:99817:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This do in remembrance of me; 1 Cor. 11.24.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Do not we hereby ſhew forth the Death of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As oft as ye eat this Bread, and drink this Cup, ye do ſhew the Lord's Death till he come; Cor 1.11.26.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>That a man may rightly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this Holy Supper, what muſt he do?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Let a man examine himſelf, and ſo let him eat of that Bread, and drink of that Cup; 1 Cor. 11.28.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>§ 5. <hi>Of Priviledges.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVHAT ſpecial Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits have we by Chriſt upon Believing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Being juſtify'd by Faith, we have peace with God; Rom. 5.1.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But when we have offended God, what muſt we do, that our ſins may be forgiven us?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:99817:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Repent and be converted; Acts 3.19.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But what hath our Saviour ſaid, ſhall become of us if we repent not?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Except ye Repent ye ſhall all — periſh; Luk. 13.3.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat other Benefits beſides Remiſſion of Sins, do we receive by Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Adoption of Sons; Gal. 4, 5.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And what do we receive hereupon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Spirit of Adoption, whereby we cry Abba Father, Rom. 8.15.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And does God hear our prayers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If we ask any thing accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Will, he heareth us; 1 Joh. 5.14.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>That you may obtain all good things then at his hand, what muſt you do?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Watch and pray; Mat, 26.4.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>That having done all theſe things, you may not fall ſhort of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99817:19"/>eternal life, what muſt you do?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Be faithfull unto death; Rev. 2.10.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Muſt you then and all men die?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is appointed unto men once to die; Heb. 9.27.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But ſhall not the dead riſe again?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As in Adam all die, even ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive; 1 Cor. 15.22.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Shall the dead then be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All that are in the graves ſhall hear his voice, and ſhall come forth; Joh. 5.28, 29.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When the dead are thus rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, what ſhall we all do?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We ſhall all ſtand before the Judgment Seat of Chriſt; Rom. 14.10.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall he then Judge all men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He will render to every man according to his deeds; Rom. 2.6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Shall not men then be call'd to account for their words?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:99817:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of every idle word that men ſhall ſpeak, they ſhall give account in the day of Judgment; Mat. 2.36.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What will God bring into Judgment at that day, beſides men's words and deeds, which have been openly ſpoken and done?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Every ſecret thing whether it be good or evill; Eccl. 12.14.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhether ſhall the Righteous go thereupon, and what ſhall become of the wicked?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Theſe ſhall go away into everlaſting puniſhment; but the Righteous into Life Eternal; Mat. 25.46.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Rev. <hi>22.20.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>He which teſtifieth theſe things, ſaith, ſurely I come quickly. Amen. Even ſo come Lord Jeſus. The Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt be with you all. Amen.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:99817:20"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Scripture-Monitor.</hi> Declaring</head>
            <p>
               <hi>The Duties of children and ſervants, which are required of them by the expreſs Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God himſelf, in his Word and Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The Duties of Children.</head>
               <p>COME, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.11.</note> ye Children, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto me: I will teach you the fear of the Lord. <hi>I will plainly tell you what the God that made you requires of you, If ye mind not theſe things to do them you deſpiſe the Word of God which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires them. And remember,</hi> Whoſo deſpiſeth the World ſhall be deſtroyed: but he that feareth the Commandment ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts,</hi> 17.31. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.14.</note> Prov. 13.13. <hi>And there is a Day of Judgment appointed, wherein God will certainly call you
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99817:20"/>to account for theſe things, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther puniſh your Contempt, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward your Obedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now if you will indeed</hi> hearken to the Voice of God, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.21.</note> hearken to the Voice of God, and obey his Will <hi>(as you muſt do, if you would go to Heaven when you die) Theſe are the Things which you muſt do.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I. You muſt honour your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, carrying your ſelf reverent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly towards them. <hi>For it is ſaid,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Honour thy Father, and thy Mother, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exo.</hi> 20.12. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.16.</note> (which is the firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment with Promiſe) that it may be well with thee, and thou may'ſt live long on the Earth. Eph. 6.2, 3.</p>
               <p n="2">II. You muſt obey your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, readily doing what they bid you to do, unleſs it be any Thing which you know is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden of God. <hi>For it is ſaid,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Children obey your Parents in the Lord: for this is right. Eph. 6.1. <hi>And again,</hi> Children, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey your Parents in all things: for this is well-pleaſing unto the Lord. Col. 3.20.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:99817:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>And remember what further Charge is given you,</hi> Do all things without Murmurings and Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, Phil. 2.24. <hi>And know, If you may not murmur, youhnuſt not rebell, Abſalom rebell'd againſt his Father, and came to an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely End.</hi> 2 Sam. 15.14. with Chap. 18.14.</p>
               <p n="3">III. You muſt hearken to the Inſtruction of your Father and Mother, and be willing to be taught by them. <hi>Saies Solomon to his Son,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Son, hear the Inſtruction of thy Father, and forſake not the Law of thy Mother. For they ſhall be an Ornament of Grace unto thy Head, and Chains about thy Neck. <hi>That is, the Virtues they teach you, will make you more lovely in the eies of all men, than the richeſt Jewels and Ornaments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. When they chaſtize you for your faults, you muſt bear this Correction with patience and humble Submiſſion; and amend what is amiſs. <hi>For ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:99817:21"/>
               <p>We had Fathers of our Fleſh, which corrected us, and we gave them reverence. Heb. 12.9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You muſt know, if they do not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect you for your faults, they do not indeed love you, For,</hi> He that ſpareth his Rod, hateth his Son: but he that loveth him chaſteneth him betimes; Prov. 13.24.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For if they ſhould let you go on in Sin without Correction, you might at length fall into Hell, and be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd without Remedy. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God hath ſaid,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With-hold not Correction from the Child: for if thou bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt him with the Rod he ſhall not die. Thou ſhalt beat him with the Rod, and deliver his Soul from Hell. Prov. 23.13, 14. <hi>And is it not better that your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents ſhould chaſtize you for your Faults with a gentle Rod, than that God ſhould deliver you up for your Crimes into the hand of the Devil, to torture you with a flaming ſcourge in the dark Manſions of Hell for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver? Its ſurely better for you to aſk Forgiveneſs for your Faults and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99817:22"/>to amend what ever is amiſs, than to murmur againſt them that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect you for your Good. It is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them you murmur but againſt God, who has commanded them to chaſtiſe you, when you do amiſs, that you may do ſo no more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And there fore if a Son was ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, and would neither hearken to the Admonition of his Father or Mother, nor be reclaim'd from his ill Courſes by their Correction, he was by Gods appointment, under the Law of Moſes, to be put to Death. For it is ſaid,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a man have a ſtubborn and rebellions Son, which will not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the Voice of his Mother, and that when they have chaſten'd him, will not hearken unto them: then ſhall his Father and his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lay hold on him, and bring him out unto the Elders of his Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and unto the gate of his Place: and they ſhall ſay unto the Elders of his City, This our Son is ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born and rebellious; he will not obey our Voice: he is a Glutton and a Drunkard. And all the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99817:22"/>men of his City ſhall ſtone him with ſtones that he die: ſo ſhalt thou put evil away from among you, and all Iſrael ſhall hear and fear. Deut. 21.18.—21.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tho' this Law doth not take place amongſt us, God is no leſs offended with ſuch ſtubbornneſs of Children now, than he was then: and therefore tho? ſuch a one may eſcape a Temporal Death, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eſcape Eternal Damnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">V. You muſt learn to know God, and be careful to ſerve him. <hi>Said David to Solomon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thou Solomon my Son, Know thou the God of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſerve Him with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Heart, and a willing Mind: for the LORD ſearcheth all Hearts, and underſtandeth all the Imaginations of the thoughts: If thou ſeek Him. He will be ſound of thee; but if thou forſake Him, He will caſt thee off for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. 1 Chro. 28.9, 10.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. You muſt not mock God's Miniſters; but obſerve them with due Reverence. <hi>Remember what
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99817:23"/>befell the Children of Bethel, who mocked the Prophet Eliſha. For,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As he was going up by the way, there came forth little Children out of the City, and mocked him, and ſaid unto him, Go up thou bald-head, go up thou bald-head. And he turned back and looked on them, and curſed them in the Name of the LORD: and there came forth two She-Bears out of the Wood, and tare fourty and two Children of them, 2 Kin. 2.23, 24.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. You muſt not mock your Parents, nor deſpiſe them; no, not in their old Age; much leſs curſe them, or ſtrike them: but cover their Infirmities, and do all you can to preſerve their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
               <p>Hearken unto thy Father, that begat thee; and deſpiſe not thy Mother, when ſhe is old. Prov. 23.22.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Remember Eli's two Sons were wicked, and they deſpiſed their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his old Age, not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his Reproof, and God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99817:23"/>them both. For it's ſaid,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eli was very old, and heard all that his Sons did unto all Iſrael, and how they laywith the women, that aſſembled at the Door of the Tabernacle of the Congregation. And he ſaid unto them, Why do ye ſuch things? For I hear of your evil Doings by all this people. Nay, my Sons; it is no good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that I hear; ye make the LORD's people to tranſgreſs. If one man ſin againſt another, the Judge ſhall judge him. But if a man ſin againſt the LORD, who ſhall entreat for him? Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they hearkened not to the Voice of their Father, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the LORD would ſlay them. 1 Sam. 2.22.25.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And accordingly it came to paſs. For</hi> the Philiſtines ſought, and Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael was ſmitten, and they fled every man into his Tent: and there was a very great ſlaughter; for there fell of Iſrael thirty Thouſand footmen. And the Ark of God was taken; and the two Sons of Eli, Hophni and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99817:24"/>Phinehas were ſlain, 1 Sam. 4.10, 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To deſpiſe the Admonition and Reproof of your Parents is a great Sin: but to mock at your Father or Mother is a greater. And therefore it is ſaid,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Eye <hi>of him</hi> that mocketh at his Father, and deſpiſeth to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey his Mother, the Ravens of the Valley ſhall pick it out, and the young Eagles ſhall eat it Prov. 30.17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is written in the Law,</hi> Curſed be he that ſetteth light by his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or his Mother: and all the people ſhall ſay; Amen. Dent. 27.15.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And,</hi> every one that curſeth his Father, or his Mother, ſhall ſurely be put to Death: he hath curſed his Father, or his Mother; his Bloud ſhall be upon hun. Lev. 20.9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And again,</hi> Whoſo curſeth his Father or his Mother, his Lamp ſhall be put out in obſecure dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Prov. 20.20. <hi>That is, he ſhall have no Child to call him Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99817:24"/>and ſo dying without Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, his Memorial ſhall periſh, and his Name ſhall be blotted out from under Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And,</hi> He that ſmiteth his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or his Mother, ſhall ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be put to Death. Exo. 21.15.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Remember how the Sons of Noah carried themſelves towards him, and take Notice why that one was Curſed, and the other Bleſſed. As it is ſaid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Noah began to be an Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, and he planted a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyard, and he drunk of the wine and was drunken, and he was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered within his Tent. And Ham, the Father of Canaan, ſaw the Nakedneſs of his Father, and told his two Brethren without. and Shem and Japheth took a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and layd it upon both their ſhoulders, and went backward, and they ſaw not their Fathers Nakedneſs. And Noah awoke from his Wine, and knew what his younger Son had done unto him. And he ſaid, Curſed be Canaan, a Servant of Servants
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99817:25"/>ſhall he be unto his Brethren. And he ſaid, Bleſſed be the LORD God of Shem; and Canaan ſhall be his Servant. God ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large Japheth, and he ſhall dwell in the Tents of Shem. Gen. 9.20—27.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. If your Parents fall into wants you muſt be ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive and ſupport them. <hi>Thus the young Storks feed and ſuſtain the old ones.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus in the years of Famine,</hi> Joſeph nouriſhed his Father, and his Brethren, and all his Fathers Houſhold with Bread, Gen. 47.12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Saviour thus blames the Phariſees;</hi> Ye ſay; If a man ſhall ſay to his Father or Mother, It is Corban, that is to ſay, a Gift <hi>[to the Temple]</hi> by whatſoever thou mighteſt be profited by me, he ſhall be free <hi>[from an Obligation to relieve them.]</hi> And ye ſuffer him no more to do ought for his Father or his Mother, making the Word of God of none effect thro' your Tradition. Mark 7.11.—13.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:99817:25"/>
               <p n="9">IX. You muſt not wrong your Parents, by taking away any thing of theirs without their Conſent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For,</hi> Whoſo robbeth his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or his Mother, and ſaith it is no Trangreſſion, the ſame is the Companion of a Deſtroyer. Prov. 28.24.</p>
               <p n="10">X. You muſt be kindly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned towards your Brethren and Siſters. There muſt be no ſtrife nor Anger amongſt you, and you muſt not call one another by any bad Names. <hi>For ſaies the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Behold how good, and how pleaſant it is for Brethren to dwell together in Unity! Pſal. 133.1.</p>
               <p>And Abram ſaid unto Lot, Let there be no Strife, I pray thee, between me and thee; for we are Brethren. Gen. 13.18.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Said Joſeph to his Brethren (whom he treated with great Kindneſs notwithſtanding their ill uſage of him)</hi> See that ye ſall not out by the way. Gen. 45.24.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mind the words of our Bleſſed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99817:26"/>Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> I ſay unto you that whoſoever is angry with his Brother without a Cauſe, ſhall be in Danger of the Judgement; and whoſoever ſhall ſay to his Brother, Raca <hi>[that is, Thou vain or empty fellow]</hi> ſhall be in danger of the Council: but who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall ſay, Thou Fool, ſhall be in Danger of Hell-fire. Mat. 5.22.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus, Children, you ſee your Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Now be it your Care to do them: And then you ſhall not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be beloved of your Parents, but God himſelf will love you, and bleſs you, and give you the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven for your Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The Duties of Servants.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>NOW you that are Servants, Know, if you will fear God and ſerve him, God will accept you and honour you; He will take you to be His Sons and Daughters, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99817:26"/>great ſhall your Reward be in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. But if not; it will not be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for you to eſcape His VVrath and Hell-fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Know then, Theſe are the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which God in his Word requires from you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I. You muſt honour your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, giving a due Reſpect to them. <hi>For ſaith the Scripture,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Son honoureth his Father, and a Servant his Maſter. Mal. 1.6. <hi>And therefore,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let as many Servants as are under the Yoke, count their own Maſters worthy of all Honour; that the Name of God and his Doctrine be not blaſphem'd. And they that have believing Maſters, let them not deſpiſe them, becauſe they are Brethren; but rather do them Service, becauſe they are faithful, and beloved, Partakers of the Benefit. 1 Tim. 6.1.2.</p>
               <p n="2">II. You muſt readily obey their lawfull Commands, without Gain-ſaying or Contradiction. <hi>For the Goſpel requires</hi> Servants to be obedient to their own Maſters,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99817:27"/>and to pleaſe them well in all Things: not anſwering again. Tit. 2.9. <hi>Again ſaith the Apoſtle,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Servants be obedient to them that are your Maſters according to the Fleſh, with Fear, and Trembling, in ſingleneſs of your Heart, as unto Chriſt. Eph. 6.5.</p>
               <p n="3">III. You muſt be ſubject to them, and ſerve them diligently and heartily. <hi>Yea, tho' your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are of a froward Diſpoſition, and hardly pleaſed, you muſt not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding be ſubject to them. For ſaith the Apoſtle,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Servants be ſubject to your Maſters with all Fear, not onely to the good and gentle, but alſo to the froward, 1 Pet. 2.18.</p>
               <p>And whatſoever ye do, do it heartily, as unto the Lord, and not unto men; knowing that of the Lord ye ſhall receive the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of Inheritance: For ye ſerve the Lord Chriſt. Col. 3.23, 24.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. You muſt be faithfull in your truſt, and not do them the leaſt Wrong in any thing.</p>
               <p>For he that doth wrong, ſhall
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99817:27"/>receive for the wrong which he hath done; and there is no reſpect of Perſons. Col. 3.25.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Servants therefore muſt be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to preſerve their Maſters Right,</hi> not purloyning, but ſhewing all good Fidelity, that they may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn the Doctrine of God our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in all things. Tit. 2.10.</p>
               <p n="5">V. You muſt be very carefull and diligent to do your Maſters work and Will, as well when he is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, as when he is preſent. <hi>For God in the Goſpel requires Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to ſerve their Maſters,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not with Eye-Service, as men-pleaſers, but as the Servants of Chriſt. Eph. 6.6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Remember when you are not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Maſters Eye, the Eye of God is upon you, who will call you to Account for whatſoever you do. Eccl.</hi> 12.14.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. You muſt carefully ſhun ill Company, and ill Courſes; as Fighting and Quarrelling, Drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and Revelling in your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Abſence, eſpecially if you have any chief Place or Charge in the Family.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:99817:28"/>
               <p>Who then is that faithfull and wiſe Servant <hi>(ſaith our Bleſſed Saviour)</hi> whom his Lord hath made Ruler over his Houſhold, to give them Meat in due Seaſon? Bleſſed is that Servant whom his Lord when he cometh, ſhall find ſo d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing. Of a truth I ſay unto you, that he will make him Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler over all that he hath. But if that evil Servant ſhall ſay in his heart, My Lord delayeth his Coming, and ſhall begin to ſmite his fellow-Servants, and to eat and drink, and to be Drunken, <hi>or</hi> to eat and drink with the Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: the Lord of that Servant <hi>[even his Lord that is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven]</hi> ſhall come in a Day when he looketh not for him, and at an Hour that he is not aware of; and ſhall cut him aſunder, [or <note n="*" place="margin">mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin</note> cut him off] and appoint him his Portion with the Hypocrites: there ſhall be weeping and gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of Teeth. Mat. 24.45.— 51. with Luk. 12.42.—46.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. If ye are rebuked, buffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or beaten by your Maſters,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99817:28"/>tho' it be without juſt cauſe, you muſt take it patiently.</p>
               <p>For this is thank worthy, if a man for Conſcience-ſake towards God, endure Grief ſuffering wrongfully. For what Glory is it, if, when ye be buffeted for your Faults, ye ſhall take it pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently? But if when ye do well and ſuffer for it, ye take it pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, this is acceptable with God. For even hereunto were you cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: becauſe Chriſt alſo ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for us, leaving us an Example that ye ſhould follow his ſteps: who did no Sin, neither was guile found in his Mouth: who when he was revil'd revil'd not again; when he ſuffered he threatned not; but committed himſelf to him that jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth righteouſly. 1 Pet 2.19.—23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus you now know your Duty: be carefull to do it; and ſo in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving your Masters, you ſhall ſerve God; and the Reward you ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from Him, will be infinitely better to you than the wages you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from them. Know, it's no ſmall Glory to be a good Servant.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99817:29"/>A Chriſtian</hi> Servant is the Lord's Free-man. <hi>Every Star ſhines in its own Sphaere. A good Servant is in God's Eye more honourable and glorious than a bad King. It's a higher Honour, a greater Glory to ſerve God, than to Command over men. If in the Diſcharge of the Duty of your Place, you faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerve Chriſt here, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12.</note> you ſhall</hi> reign with him <hi>in Heaven,</hi> to whom be Glory for ever and ever, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.5.</note> Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:99817:29"/>
            <head>A <hi>Catechiſm for Communicants:</hi> WHEREIN <hi>The Nature and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtiament</hi> are explain'd, for the <hi>Inſtruction</hi> of thoſe who are of competent Age, to receive the Holy <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Lord's Supper.</hi>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVHAT doth God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of man in Order to his Salvation and eternal Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.46.47.</note> The ſerious Exerciſe of the true Religion.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is that true Religion, which is the onely ſure way to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2, 13, 14, 15,</note> The Chriſtian Religion, which was inſtituted by Chriſt himſelf, and is preſcrib'd in his Holy Goſpel.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:99817:30"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doth the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion comprehend?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Faith, Obedience, Prayer, and Sacraments.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the Sum of your Faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I believe in God, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Almighty, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How muſt you manifeſt the Truth of your Faith?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.18</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By Obedience.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the Rule of your O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Law of God, which is briefly comprehended in Ten Commandments.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.9, 10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.31. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Rehearſe them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God ſpake all theſe Words, ſaying, I am the LORD thy God, &amp;c. Exod. 20.1—17.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Have you kept all theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Exod.</hi> 36.27.</note> No, I have not; neither can I ſo keep them as I ought, without the help of God's Grace.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What muſt you then do?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.2.</note> Earneſtly pray to God for pardon, and Grace.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:99817:30"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the moſt excellent Pattern of your Prayers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Lord's Prayer.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Rehearſe it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Our Father, which art in Heaven, &amp;c. Mat. 6.9—13.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In whoſe Name and Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation muſt you make your Addreſſes to God in your Prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.23, 24. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.22. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Jum.</hi> 5.16</note> In the Name of our onely Mediator, Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But how muſt you pray that you may prevail?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I muſt pray in Faith, with Fervency of ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the Ground of your Faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Word and Promiſes of God.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Hath God afforded you any ſpecial Helps of Faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yes, the Sacraments.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat are the Sacraments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Signs of things not ſeen, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4, 11</note> Seals of the Covenant of Grace, and viſible Pledges of the Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of all God's Promiſes.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhy were they appointed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That Faith might be relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99817:31"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:99817:31"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:99817:32"/>by Sight, and Devotion aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted by Senſe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many Sacraments are there?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Onely two, Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Of what ſpecial <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe are theſe to us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41 42 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12, 13.</note> By Baptiſm we have Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion into the Church, and hold Communion with it in the Lord's Supper.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But what's their different <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe in reſpect of the Covenant of Grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. By Baptiſm we enter into Covenant with God, and renew it in the Lord's Supper.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How elſe do they differ?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.48—58.</note> Baptiſm is a Sacrament of our New Birth, and the Lord's Supper of our ſpiritual Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and growth in Grace.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How oft muſt we receive theſe Sacraments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Baptiſm but once; the Lord's Supper often: for we can be but once born, but muſt be oft fed.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:99817:32"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>What muſt we conſider in the Sacraments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The outward Signs, the Things thereby ſignify'd, and the ſpiritual Benefits thereof.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the outward Sign in Baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Water. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.23. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.36, 38. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25, 26.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat doth the VVater in Baptiſm ſignify?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The renewing Grace and purifying Virtue of the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doth the waſhing of the Body with water ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 22.16.</note> The cleanſing of the Soul from Sin.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the Spiritual Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of Baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. A Regeneration, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5;</note> or a New Birth.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat mean you by Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, or the New Birth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. A Change of our Nature, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11.</note> which being depraved by Sin, is therein renew'd by the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is Baptiſm to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, and by whom?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:99817:33"/>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19.</note> By the Miniſters of Chriſt, in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVho are to be Baptiz'd</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 39.</note> Converts to the Chriſtian Religion, and the Children of Chriſtians</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>To what are we bound by our Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3—13.</note> To forſake our Sins, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Chriſt, and lead our Lives according to the Laws of God, and Rules of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherein ſtands the Lord's Supper, and how is it to be celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26, 27. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.19, 20.</note> In a ſolemn bleſſing, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and cating of Bread, and Drinking of Wine, with Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, in Remembrance of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the Intent and Meaning of this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28.</note> The ſetting forth of the Death and ſufferings of Chriſt, whoſe Body was broken on the Croſs, and his Bloud ſhed for our Sins.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat are the outward Signs in the Lord's Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:99817:33"/>
            <p>A. Bread and Wine. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26, 27.28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What do this ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The Body and Bloud of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Hath Jeſus Chriſt a true Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yes; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21.</note> the ſame Body which was crucified on Earth, is glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Q. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk</hi> 22.19, 20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.39.</note> 
               <hi>Is the Bread in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the very Body of Chriſt, and the Wine his Bloud?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. No; they are but the ſigns of his Body and Bloud, and Pled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Benefits we receive thereby. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doth the breaking of the Bread ſignifie?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A. The breaking of Chriſt's Body in his Crucifixion.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doth the Miniſter's giving the Bread and Wine to the Communicants repreſent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Chriſt's giving himſelf, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 22; 19.</note> with the Benefits of his Body and Bloud, to Believers.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat doth the receiving, eating, and drunking ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Our receiving and apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:99817:34"/>of Chriſt, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.48—58.</note> and his Benefits to our ſelves by Faith.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the Benefits of this Holy Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.28.</note> Remiſſion of Sins, and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What mean you by the New Teſtament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.15, 16.</note> The Covenant of Grace under the Evangelical Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, which is now eſtabliſht as the laſt Will and Teſtament of Jefus Chriſt, whereby he hath bequeath'd unto us an eternal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What follows upon the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.8, 9.10.</note> An aſſured Right to all the Bleſſings of the Covenant, with a renewed Obligation to Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: for herein Chriſt gives himſelf with all the Benefits of his Death to me; and I give my ſelf up to ſerve him all the Daies of my life.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How muſt you receive this Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22—29.</note> With great Reverence and Devotion, in Remembrance of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:99817:34"/>Chriſt crucified, who is herein lively ſet forth before mine eies,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24, 25. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1.</note> as broken, bleeding, dying on the Croſs.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But that you may be meet to receive it, and partake of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits thereof, what muſt you do?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. I muſt examine my ſelf, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28.</note> concerning my ſpiritual State.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Herein what muſt you chiefly inquire after?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Whether I conſent to the Covenant of Grace, lead my life according to the Law of God, and obey the Commands of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.</p>
            <p>Q. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33. with <hi>Heb</hi> 8.10.</note> 
               <hi>What is the Tenour of the Covenant of Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What does the Law of God require of you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.2, 3, 8, 12.</note> To acknowledge the true God, and worſhip him alone as God; to fanctifie the Sabbath, and honour my Parents.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>And what does it forbid?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Idolatry, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.4, 5, 7, 13—17.</note> and Abuſe of God's Name, Murder, Adultery,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:99817:35"/>Theſt, Lying, and coveting what is another man's.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What does God in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel require of you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 1.15. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.23. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7.</note> Repentance, and Faith; Brotherly Love, and Charity.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In examining your ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe Evangelical Graces, what muſt you inquire?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10, 11.</note> Whether I am heartily ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for all my ſins, and ſtedfaſtly reſolved to lead a new Life; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal,</hi> 3.21, 22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.12. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.31. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.8.</note> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſtedfaſtly believe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the Goſpel, and put my whole Truſt in Chriſt for my Salvation; whether I unfeigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly love the Children of God, as my Brethren in Chriſt, and am in Charity with all men.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But wherein muſt you exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe this Charity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.14, 15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.20, 21. <hi>Epb.</hi> 4.28. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10.</note> In loving mine Enemies, in forgiving of Wrongs, in doing Good againſt Evil, in releiving (according to my Ability) them that are in want, and doing Good (as I have opportunity) to all men.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But why are theſe Graces of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99817:35"/>Faith, and Brotherly Love, and Charity, eſpecially required for the right receiving of the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.28. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.47. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.34. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.14.</note> Becauſe the Bloud of Chriſt is therein exhibited for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Sins, and without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance there is no Remiſſion; and if we do not from our Hearts for give them that have treſpaſſed againſt us (which is an Act of Chriſtian Charity) God will not forgive our Treſpaſſes againſt him: And laſtly, nothing can be more neceſſary than brotherly Love in the Lord's Supper, which is a Feaſt of Loves, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Gen.</hi> 43.16.</note> wherein (as the Brethren of Joſeph, with him.) we feaſt with our Elder Brother, Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>When you have thus exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd your ſelf concerning your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual State, what muſt you further do, that you may rightly receive this Holy Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5, 6.</note> I muſt caſt my ſelf down before God, and with Sorrow in my Heart, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.9.</note> make an humble Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:99817:36"/>of my Sins, and earneſtly implore Mercy in the free pardon of them in the Bloud of my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.10.</note> I muſt bewail my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and wants, and earneſtly crave of God thoſe Aids and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of his Grace, which may enable me to honour him by a Holy Obedience for the time to come; I muſt put forth in my Soul the Acts of Faith, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.6.</note> brotherly Love and Charity, and ſtir up in my Heart hungring Deſires after Chriſt, and the Participation of his ſaving Benefits in his Holy Supper.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why muſt you thus examine and prepare your ſelf, before you come to the Lord's Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Leſt I ſhould receive it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the Sin and Danger of unworthy receiving?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27, 28.</note> He that receiveth unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily is guilty of the Body and Bloud of the Lord (as the wicked Jews, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 7.52.</note> who were his Betrayers and Murderers) and eateth and Drinketh <note n="*" place="margin">Gr. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>render'd in the Marg. Judgment. See v.</hi> 30, 31, 32.</note> Judgment or Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:99817:36"/>to himſelf, being for this Sin liable to temporal Afflictions, yea, to eternal Damnation, in the juſt Judgment of God.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>When doth a man receive unworthily?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. When he preſumeth to come to the Lord's Table in the guilt of any known Sin unrepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, or wanting that Faith, Love, and Charity, which are required in a worthy Receiver.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>If the Sin and Danger of unworthy Receiving be ſo great, is it not ſafer to forbear, than to come to the Lord's Table?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. He that forbears to come to the Lord's Table, incurs a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter guilt and Danger: for to the guilt that would make him an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Receiver, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.19.</note> he adds the Contempt of Chriſt's Command, and of the Benefits of his Bloud, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.</note> freely offer'd to him in this Holy Supper.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What then muſt you do, that you keep your ſelf clear from this Guilt, and ſafe from this Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:99817:37"/>
            <p>A. I muſt be very carefull and ſerious in examining my ſelf, and finding my ſelf guilty,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28, 31.</note> I muſt judge and condemn my ſelf, that I may be graciouſly acquitted by the Lord, and accepted as a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Receiver.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>If you rightly receive this Bleſſed Sacrament, what Benefit ſhall you have thereby?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.28.</note> God will ſeal to my Soul the Pardon of all my Sins in the Bloud of Chriſt, with a Right to all the Bleſſings and Priviledges of the Covenant of Grace.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>If after you have received this Holy Sacrament, you ſhould return to your former ſins, what will your State and Condition be?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.20. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.28, 29. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20, 21, 22.</note> VVorſe than before: For I ſhall greatly provoke the wrath of God, by the Breach of a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Covenant, ratifi'd with the Bloud of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How muſt you demean your ſelf then after you have received?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.18 <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6, 7.</note> I muſt carefully keep my ſelf from Sin, that Sin eſpecially to which I am moſt inclin'd; and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:99817:37"/>humbly walk with God in the ways of Holineſs, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.23.</note> being diligent in every good Duty.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What will be the Iſſue of this Holy Courſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. I ſhall at length ſee my Bleſſed Saviour Jeſus Chriſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in Heaven,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.22—24.</note> who was Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d for me on Earth, and ſhall for ever live and reign with him in Glory.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>COL. <hi>11.6, 7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>As ye have therefore received Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, ſo walk ye in Him: rooted and built up in Him, and eſtabliſhed in the Faith, as ye have been taught, abounding therein with Thanksgiving.</p>
            </q>
            <p>If any by reaſon of the <hi>Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Memory,</hi> or want of Ability to read, cannot learn by Heart the fore-going Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſin, that they may not be kept from the Lord's Table, nor come
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:99817:38"/>unprepar'd, I have comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the moſt <hi>neceſſary things</hi> in the following Abridgment. Let ſuch then, when they can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat the <hi>Creed, the ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the Lord's Prayer,</hi> learn this <hi>Shorter Catechiſm.</hi> But if they learn this onely at their firſt Admiſſion, they ſhall do well for an <hi>Increaſe of Knowledge,</hi> to endeavour to learn the other alſo, for their greater Benefit in their after-receiving.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:99817:38"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Shorter Catechiſm</hi> for the Younger Communicants.</head>
            <p>Q. <hi>WHAT Religion is the onely ſure way to Salvation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doth the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion comprehend?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Faith, Obedience, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and Sacraments</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the Sum of your Faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I believe in God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Almighty, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the Rule of your O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Law of God which is comprehended in Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Rehearſe them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God ſpake all theſe Words, &amp;c. Exo. 20.1—17.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:99817:39"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the Pattern of your Prayers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Lord's Prayer.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Rehearſe it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Our Father, which art in Heaven, &amp;c. Mat. 6.9—13.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the Sacraments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Seals of the Covenant of Grace.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the Tenour of the Covenant of Grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I will be their God, and they ſhall be my People.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many Sacraments are there?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Onely two; Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Of what <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe are theſe to us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By Baptiſm we enter into Covenant with God, and renew it in the Lord's Supper.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How elſe do they differ?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Baptiſm is a Sacrament of our New Birth; the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of our Spiritual Nouriſhment and Growth in Grace.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How oft muſt we receive them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Baptiſm but once, the Lord's
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:99817:39"/>Supper often: for we can be but once born, but muſt be oft fed.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What muſt we conſider in the Sacraments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The outward Signs, the Things thereby ſignifi'd, and the ſpiritual Benefits thereof.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the outward Sign in Baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Water.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doth the water in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Grace of God's Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat doth the waſhing of the Body with water ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The cleanſing of the Soul from Sin.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the Benefit of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Regeneration, or a New Birth.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is Regeneration?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A Renewing of the Nature of man, by the Spirit and Grace of God.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In whoſe Name is Baptiſm to be Adminiſtred?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In the Name of the Father,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:99817:40"/>and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVho are to be Baptiz'd?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Converts to the Chriſtian Religion, and the Children of Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>To what are you bound by your Baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To forſake my Sins, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Chriſt, and obey him.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat are the outward Signs in the Lord's Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Bread and Wine.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat do they ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Body and Bloud of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Hath Chriſt a true Body?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes; the ſame Body which was crucified on Earth, is glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is the Bread in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the very Body of Chriſt, and the Wine his Bloud?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No; They are but the Signs of his Body and Bloud.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doth the breaking of the Bread ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Breaking of Chriſt's Body in his Crucifixion.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:99817:40"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doth the Miniſter's gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Bread and Wine to the Communicants repreſent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God's giving of Chriſt, and His Benefits to Believers.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doth the receiving, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and Drinking ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Our receiving and apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt by Faith.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the Benefits of this Holy Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The ſtrengthening and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing of our Souls by Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Chriſt in the Graces and Comforts of his Spirit.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was this Sacrament inſtituted?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To ſhew forth the Death of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How muſt we receive it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In Remembrance of him.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But that you may receive it aright what muſt you do?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Examine my ſelf whether I live in any Sin.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe if I live in any known Sin I ſhall be an unworthy Receiver.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:99817:41"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the Sin and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of unworthy Receiving?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He that receiveth unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily is guilty of the Body and Bloud of the Lord, and eateth and drinketh Damnation to himſelf.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What muſt you then do?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Repent of my Sins, and reſolve to lead a new Life.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But with what Graces must you be furniſht, that you may be fit to come to the Lord's Table?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> With Faith in Chriſt, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly Love, and Charity.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherein muſt you ſpecially ſhew this Charity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In loving mine Enemies, doing good to them that hate me, and forgiving them that wrong me.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>If you rightly receive this Bleſſed Sacrament, what Benefit ſhall you have thereby?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God will ſeal up to me the Pardon of my Sins, and the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of my Soul.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But how muſt you demean your ſelf after you have received?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. I muſt carefully keep my ſelt
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:99817:41"/>from every known Sin, and be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in every good Duty.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What will be the Iſſue of this Holy-Courſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A I ſhall at length ſee my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in Heaven, and for ever live, and reign with him in Glory.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Joh. <hi>14.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>If ye love me, keep my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:99817:42"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Self-Examination,</hi> Directed by way of Example: wherein The Qualification of a Worthy Communicant is diſcloſed by the Anſwer of a good Conſcience, to ſome Neceſſary Inquiries.</head>
            <head type="sub"> The Apoſtle's Precept.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. 11.28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Let a mau EXAMIN himſelf, and ſo let him eat of that Bread, and drink of that Cup.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>The Chriſtians Practice.</head>
            <p>IHAVE now an Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of receiving the <hi>Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi> of the LORD'S SUPPER. I cannot neglect it without the Guilt of a great Sin; the Breach of Chriſt's Command,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.10.</note> who hath ſaid, <hi>This do in Remembrance of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:99817:42"/>me;</hi> yea, the Contempt of <hi>Chriſt crucifid,</hi> who therein offers him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf freely, with all the Benefits of his Body and Bloud, to my Soul; and the Reſuſal of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newall of my Covenant</hi> with God, whereby as I am bound to a <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Obedience,</hi> ſo I am aſſured of <hi>everlaſting Bleſsednefs.</hi> And yet if I receive it <hi>unworthily,</hi> I ſhall be <hi>guilty of the body and Bloud of the Lord,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27.29.</note> and eat and drink to my ſelf Judgment,</hi> and become liable to <hi>Damnation.</hi> Yet I know the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of my Duty, is no way to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape this Danger. But the way both to eſcape the Danger, and to enjoy the Benefit, is to <hi>Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine my ſelf,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11, 28.</note> and ſo to come to the Lord's Table. This then, with the Help of God, will I do. I will here ſet my ſelf as before God, and as in his ſight and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence <hi>examine my ſelf,</hi> as he hath commanded.</p>
            <p>Now the Lord direct and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt me in this Work, that I may ſo know the State of my own Soul, as that I may rightly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:99817:43"/>my ſelf for the receiving of the Bleſſed Sacrament of Chriſt's Holy Supper, and the Participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ineſtimable Benefits of his Body and Bloud.</p>
            <p>This Holy Supper, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25.</note> I know, is a Seal of the Covenant of Grace, or <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> which is rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd in the <hi>Bloud</hi> of my Saviour. Now if I rightly receive this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, I muſt heartily <hi>conſent to this Covenant,</hi> the Tenour whereof is this; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.22. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10.</note> 
               <hi>Ye ſahll be my People and I will be your God.</hi> Now,</p>
            <p>Q. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of</hi> 1 <hi>Conſent to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. Pſal.</hi> 42. 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 37.26.</note> 1. <hi>Do I heartily take God for my God, and am I really wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be one of his People? Am I really willing to renounce all my Luſts and Sins, and to love, ſerve, honour, and obey God all the daies of my Life; and do I reſt ſatisfi'd in Him, as</hi> my God and my Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> O Lord my God! I have grievouſly ſinned againſt Thee; I have <hi>forgotten Thee Daies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Number:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.32.</note> but now I return to Thee, and here moſt ſeriouſly
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:99817:43"/>and heartily give my ſelf up to Thee, both Body and Soul, to be Thine for ever. I deſire not to live a Day longer, than I may ſerve and glorifie Thee. I hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rejoyce that Thou art pleaſed to give thy ſelf to me, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40.</note> 
               <hi>by an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant,</hi> to be my God and Portion, my <hi>Shield and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great Reward.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1.</note> I thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully take Thee to be my God, and I reſt fully ſatisfied in Thee, as <hi>the chief eſt Good,</hi> and my one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Happineſs. For <hi>whom have I in Heaven</hi> O God! <hi>but Thee? <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25.</note> And there is none upon Earth that I deſire beſides Thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, alas! I am a guilty Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. But having now a happy Opportunity of getting the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of all my Sins ſeal'd to me, in the Bloud of my Saviour, I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to review the Actions of my Life, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.40.</note> and to make a <hi>diligent Search</hi> for the Diſcovery of my Sins, that upon my <hi>penitent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi> of them, I may obtain a <hi>gracious Pardon,</hi> according to God's faithfull Promiſe, who hath
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:99817:44"/>ſaid, <hi>He that cooereth his Sins ſhall not proſper, but whoſo confeſſeth and for ſaketh them, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.13.</note> ſhall have Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <note place="margin">2, <hi>Sin.</hi>
               </note> 2. <hi>What then are the Sins I am guilty of before God? If I was ſure I ſhould not live to ſee the Light of another Day, what Sin would make me affraid to die? What</hi> Good <hi>have I omitted that I might and ought to have done? What</hi> Evil <hi>have I committed? Wherein have I tranſgreſs'd, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended God, the Great Governour, and Juſt Judge of the whole World, in whoſe Hand my Life is? Ah Lord!</hi> How many are mine Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities and my Sins? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.23.</note> 
               <hi>Oh that God would</hi> make me, to know my Tranſgreſſions, <hi>and ſhew me</hi> my Sins! <hi>And then as for theſe</hi> Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of my Soul, <hi>Oh that (as the</hi> Egyptians in the Red Sea) <hi>they might be all deſtroy'd by my</hi> Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13.</note> 
               <hi>that henceforth I might</hi> ſee them again no more for ever.</p>
            <p>For the finding of them out, in Order to this End, I will now
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:99817:44"/>make a diligent Enquiry. And for the Diſcovery of my Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, I will lay the <hi>Law of God,</hi> even the <hi>Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> before me, and conſider whether I have led my Life ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God's Law, or not.</p>
            <p>GOD hath ſaid in his LAW, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.2, 3, 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>I am the LORD thy God, &amp;c. Thou ſhalt have no other Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me. Thou ſhalt not make unto Thee any graven Image, &amp;c.</hi> See Exod. 20. 1—17. Now</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Breach of</hi> 1. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.15, 16.</note> Have I ſo taken God for my God, as to love and honour Him above all? Have I not <hi>loved the World, and the Things of the World,</hi> Riches and Honours, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and worldly Delights, more than God? Have I not lived in much <hi>Forgetfulneſs</hi> of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.32.</note> and <hi>eſtrangement</hi> from Him? Have I not <hi>feared</hi> men more than God? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.28.</note> Have I not ſet my ſelf up above God, ſerving <hi>my own Will,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.30. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.1, 2, 3.</note> more than His; and ſeeking <hi>to pleaſe my ſelf</hi> more than him?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Tho' I have not worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped Idols, <note place="margin">II. Com.</note> ave I not neglected
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:99817:45"/>the Worſhip of God, or ſhew'd leſs Reverence to Him, than the poor Pagans do to dead and dumb Idols? Have I diligently attended the <hi>Ordinances of God's Worſhip,</hi> and ſo demeaned my ſelf therein, as under his Eye? Have I watch'd over my Heart, and not ſuffer'd my Thoughts to wander from the Holy Service I have had in Hand? Have I been very ſerious and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere in the Service of God? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.13.</note> Have I not oft <hi>drawn near to God with my Mouth, and honour'd him with my Lips, when my Heart hath been removed ſar from Him?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">III. <hi>Com.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Have I not taken the Name of God in vain, uſing it lightly and cuſtomarily in my Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, ſaying, <hi>O Lord, and O God,</hi> when I have not thought of Him; or abuſing it in <hi>Oaths and Curſes?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34.</note> Has my Heart accompanied my Tongue as oft as I have uſed the Name of God in my Prayers? Have I never made a Jeſt of any Thing that is Sacred? Have I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd ſo <hi>to adorn the Doctrine of God my Saviour in all things, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.10.</note>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:99817:45"/>that the Name of God might not, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.1.</note> thro' me, be blaſphem'd by</hi> any?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Have I remembred God's Day, <note place="margin">IV. Com.</note> and diſpoſed my ſelf to the keeping of it Holy? Have I with as much Diligence and Seriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Conſtance, and Chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, attended the Service of God, and the bleſſed Means of the Salvation of my Soul, on the <hi>Lord's Day,</hi> as I have my world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Buſineſs or Diſports on my own Daies? Have I not been ſoon <hi>weary</hi> of the Service and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Am.</hi> 8.5.</note> wiſhing the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ended, and the <hi>Sabbath done,</hi> that I might be let looſe to my worldly Employments or Recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations? Have I not oft ſpent the moſt part of that Day, which is conſecrated to the Service of God, in idle Talk, or worldly matters, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.13.</note> or carnall Delights, without ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious minding of the great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of my immortal Soul. <note place="margin">V. Com.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Have I ſo honour'd and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey'd my Father and Mother, my Maſter and Superiours, as I ought to have done? Have I not
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:99817:46"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:99817:46"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:99817:47"/>deſpiſed their Authority, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to obey their Commands?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.14.</note> Have I <hi>done all things without Murmurings and Diſputings?</hi> Have I hearkened to their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions, and received their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs without Cavilling; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.9.</note> or <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering again?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>VI. Com. Mat.</hi> 5.22. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.15.</note> Tho' I have not been guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of groſs Murder, or killing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny body, yet have I not <hi>been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with my Brother without a Cauſe?</hi> Have I not <hi>hated him in my Heart,</hi> and ſo been a <hi>Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> in the Sight of God? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.18. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.19. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.13.</note> Have I not been given to Quarrelling and Contention? Have I not given provoking Words? And when I have thought my ſelf wrong'd, have I not born <hi>Malice</hi> in my Heart, and meditated <hi>Revenge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <note place="margin">VII. Com.</note> Have I not by wanton Looks or Geſtures, Words or Thoughts, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.27, 28.</note> 
               <hi>committed Adultery in my Heart,</hi> or by any vile Acts or Provocations of Luſt, made my ſelf unclean in the Sight of God? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.19.</note> Have I endeavour'd by Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Sobriety, to keep my
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:99817:47"/>Body pure, and my Mind chaſt and undefiled? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3.8.</note> Have no vile Luſts lodg'd in my Heart, and has <hi>no filthy Communication</hi> at any time <hi>come out of my mouth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. <note place="margin">VIII. Com.</note> Have I injur'd any one by Theft, Deceipt, or Couſenage? Have I been juſt and true in all my Truſts and Dealings? Have I not waſted much Time in ſloth, Idleneſs, and Vanity? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.28.</note> Have I not waſted what I had in Sports and Gaming? Have I not <hi>conſented</hi> to or conceal'd the Frauds or Wrongs that have been done by others? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.18.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. <note place="margin">IX. Com.</note> Have I not been guilty of Lying and Slandering? Have I not taken pleaſure in hearing my Neighbour <hi>reproacht</hi> and evil ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of behind his back? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.3.</note> Have I not abetted to the injuries done him by others, by bearing falſe witneſs againſt him? Have I not ſometimes ſcoft at men for thoſe Infirmities, which I ought to have <hi>cover'd in Love?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4 8.</note> Have I been carefull to keep my word, and to perform all my Promiſes to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man?</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:99817:48"/>
            <p n="10">10. <note place="margin">X. Com.</note> Have I been truly content with my own State and Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without coveting any Thing which is another man's? Have <hi>I</hi> not envy'd others their Happier Eſtate, and repin'd at the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my own Condition? Have <hi>I</hi> not more complain'd of the Wants and Evils <hi>I</hi> have ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd according to my Deſerts, than <hi>I</hi> have been thankfull for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny undeſerved Mercies and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.2.</note> I</hi> confeſs <hi>I</hi> have <hi>offended in many Things. I</hi> am guilty of very many Tranſgreſſions, in ſo much as if God ſhould <hi>enter into Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> with me, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.2.</note> He might moſt juſtly condemn me. But <hi>I</hi> hope in His Mercy, who hath promiſed <hi>Pardon</hi> to all that truly <hi>repent.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19.</note> But</p>
            <p>Q. <note place="margin">3. <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Do I truly and heartily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of all my Sins, and am I ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly reſolved, by the Grace of God, to lead a new Life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. I</hi> am heartily ſorry for all my Sins, which <hi>I</hi> have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt that God to whom <hi>I</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:99817:48"/>owe my Life and Being, and who hath been very good and gracious to me all my Life long; and I do ſtedfaſtly reſolve forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to forſake all my Sins, and to endeavour to lead my Life in all Things according to the Holy Law of God, and Rules of the Goſpel, for the Time to come; and I do heartily beſeech Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God to enable me by his Grace ſo to do.</p>
            <p>Q. 4. <note place="margin">4, <hi>Faith in Chriſt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Do I believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt? Am I fully perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that He is the Son of God, and Saviour of the World; and that all. He hath revealed and ſaid in his Holy Goſpel is moſt certainly true? Do I heartily take Him for my Lord and Redeemer, and truſt in Him alone for my Salvation? <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.18.</note> And</hi> can I ſhew my Faith by my Works?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I do ſtedfaſtly Believe that God <hi>the Father ſent his Son to be the Saviour of the World;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37.</note> that <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> who died at Jeruſalem, <hi>is the Son of God;</hi> and I do hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily take Him to be my <hi>Lord and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6.</note>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:99817:49"/>Saviour;</hi> and ſubmitting my ſelf to his Soveraignty, I truſt in Him alone for my Salvation. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 1.15.</note> I am ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſuaded that whatſoever He hath ſaid or revealed in his <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel</hi> is moſt true. And I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, by God's Grace, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in this <hi>Faith,</hi> and to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the Truth of it by my <hi>Works,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.18</note> and conſtant Obedience to His Holy Commands all the daies of my Life.</p>
            <p>Q. 5. <note place="margin">5. <hi>Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Love.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Do I entirely love all the Children of God, as my Brethren in Chriſt, even becauſe they are God's Children, bear His Image and are beloved by their Heavenly Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I have a Love for all men, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.9.</note> and do Deſire to <hi>love my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as myſelf;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.14.</note> but for thoſe who truly fear-God, I have a great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of them, and a hearty <hi>Love</hi> to them; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.3.</note> I account them <hi>the onely excellent Ones in the Earth.</hi> And the more excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy <hi>I</hi> ſee in them, the more my Heart is endeared to them. <hi>I</hi> chiefly delight in their Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; and when <hi>I</hi> can enjoy mine
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:99817:49"/>own Choice, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pſal.</hi> 119.63.</note> 
               <hi>I am a Companion of them that fear God, and keep his Commandments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. 6. <note place="margin">6. <hi>Charity. Luk.</hi> 6.37. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>Am I in Charity with all men? Can I freely</hi> forgive <hi>them that have wrong'd me, and find in my Heart to</hi> do good to them who hate me, <hi>and ahve done and would do me Hurt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. I</hi> thank God, <hi>I</hi> bear no <hi>Malice</hi> in my Heart to any man. <hi>I</hi> do <hi>freely forgive</hi> them who have wrong'd me, and account it but a very ſmall matter, if my Lord will graciouſly be pleaſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me <hi>a Debt of Ten Thouſand Talents,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.23—35.</note> to forgive to my fellow-Servant <hi>a Debt of an Hundred pence.</hi> And God knows my heart if it lay in my power, <hi>I</hi> could free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>do Good</hi> to the worſt Enemy <hi>I</hi> have in the World. If he was in <hi>Danger, I</hi> would do my beſt to <hi>preſerve</hi> him: If <hi>I</hi> knew him to be in any <hi>Extremity, I</hi> would to my Ability, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.20.</note> very freely <hi>relieve</hi> Him. <hi>I</hi> know <hi>I</hi> more need mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy from God, than any man can need Mercy from me: and <hi>I</hi> am
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:99817:50"/>ready and willing <hi>to ſhew Mercy</hi> to any man, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.13.</note> as <hi>I</hi> do expect and deſire to <hi>obtain Mercy</hi> from God, in the Forgiveneſs of my Sins, and the Salvation of my Soul.</p>
            <p>Q. <note place="margin">7. <hi>Defire of Chriſt.</hi>
               </note> 7. <hi>Have I an Appetite to my Spiritual Food? Have I an earneſt Defire to have Communion with Chriſt, and to partake of his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Benefits in his Holy Supper.?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Without Chriſt, alas! <hi>I</hi> am an undone Creature. Ah Lord God! What wilt thou give me, if <hi>I</hi> go Chriſtleſs? Give me therefore, O give me Chriſt, or <hi>I</hi> die. It is Pardon, and Grace, and ſpiritual ſtrength, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, which he is pleaſed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to Believers in his Holy Supper. Theſe <hi>I</hi> want; theſe <hi>I</hi> earneſtly defire. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10.</note> 
               <hi>I</hi> muſt have <hi>Pardon,</hi> or periſh: Without <hi>Grace I</hi> can do no good. <hi>Peace</hi> with God is an ineſtimable Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: without this <hi>I</hi> cannot hope to ſee His Face in Heaven. <hi>I</hi> want <hi>Strength</hi> to do my Duties, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer my Corruptions, bear my Burdens, and withſtand my
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:99817:50"/>Temptations. And my Soul thirſts after thoſe <hi>Holy Comforts,</hi> which are far ſweeter than all <hi>worldly Joys.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal,</hi> 4.7.</note> Theſe are the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings I earneſtly defire. Theſe are the Benefits of my Bleſſed Lord and Suviour Jeſus Chriſt. And I am willing to part with the Pleaſures of Sin for ever, to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of theſe Holy Comforts; and there is no Treaſure in the whole World that I prize or deſire in compariſon of theſe ineſtimable Priviledges, which I beſeech God to communicate to me in this <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Feaſt.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.5 <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.47. <hi>Jude v.</hi> 25.</note> So ſhall <hi>my Soul be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfi'd as with Marrow and Fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and I ſhall greatly rejoyce in God my Saviour, to whom be Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Majesty, Dominion and Power, both now and ever. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now if upon this ſerious</hi> Self-Examination, <hi>thou canſt from thy Heart make theſe</hi> Anſwers <hi>to theſe</hi> Queſtions, <hi>doubt not but God will accept thee as a worthy</hi> Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:99817:51"/>
               <hi>and thou ſhalt be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Gueſt <hi>to the</hi> Lord's Table. <hi>God in that Bleſſed Ordinance of Chriſt's</hi> Holy Supper, <hi>will ſeal up to thy Soul the Pardon of all thy ſins, and that</hi> Covenant of Grace. <hi>whereby he aſſures thee of a Kingdome of Glory for thine etenal Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conclude this Work of</hi> Self-Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination <hi>with that</hi> Confeſſion and Prayer, <hi>which is fitted for that Purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:99817:51"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Chriſtian-Devotion.</hi> IN <hi>Some ſhort Forms of PRAYER &amp; PRAISE.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Prayers for Children.</head>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A Prayer for the Morning.</head>
                  <p>O LORD God, and my Heavenly Father, <hi>I</hi> give Thee humble and hearty Thanks, for that Thou haſt preſerved me this Night paſt, and raiſ'd me up in Health and Strength this Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; whereas Thou mighteſt in the Darkneſs of the Night, have cut me off for my Sins, and caſt me into everlaſting Darkneſs in Hell. Pardon, O Lord, all my paſt Sins, and keep me from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for the time to come.</p>
                  <p>Guide, bleſs, and keep me
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:99817:52"/>this Day in Thy Fear; and grant that <hi>I</hi> may demean my ſelf alwaies as in thy Sight. And ſeeing <hi>I</hi> muſt at length appear before the Judgment Seat of Chriſt, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive according to my Works, and muſt then give an Account of every idle VVord, grant that <hi>I</hi> may keep my ſelf this Day from all fooliſh-ſpeaking &amp; evil-doing: Eſpecially grant that <hi>I</hi> may keep my Heart with all Diligence, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of it come thoſe evil Things which defile both Body and Soul.</p>
                  <p>Keep me, O Lord, by thy Grace, from all wanton thoughts, Words, and Looks, and from all thoſe fleſhly Luſts, which will defile my Soul, and make me loathſome in thy Sight. Oh keep me from my ſpecial ſin, and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me to every good Duty. Keep me from miſpending my precious Time in Vanity and Idleneſs, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon this little Moment of my Life depends an Eternity of Joy or Torment.</p>
                  <p>Sanctifie me throughout by
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:99817:52"/>Thy Holy Spirit, and enable me by thy Grace to live to thy Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Plant in my Heart a Hatred of Sin and Love to Holineſs; that I may <hi>delight to do Thy Will O my God!</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.8. <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.34.</note> and account it <hi>my Meat</hi> and Drink to be employ'd in well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing.</p>
                  <p>Grant I may love Thee with all my Heart and Soul, and ſerve Thee with all my Strength, all the Daies of my Life; that in the End I may be happy for ever.</p>
                  <p>Make me like Chriſt in meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Patience, Humility, that I may be like to Him hereafter in Glory.</p>
                  <p>Keep me this Day from Sin and Danger, and give me all things both for my Soul and Body, which Thou ſeeſt to be needfull and good for me. Make me e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Thankfull for Thy Mercies, and truly contented with my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Do good, O Lord, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.4.</note> to them that are good,</hi> and convert Sinners from their evil waies that they may be ſaved. Bleſs my Parents;
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:99817:53"/>Give them Health, Proſperity, and Length of Days here, and everlaſting Happineſs in Heaven. Bleſs all my Friends and dear Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; give them Grace and all good things both for Body and Soul.</p>
                  <p>Bleſs me, even me alſo, O my Father, with the Bleſſings of thy Love and guide me in thy Holy ways to Life eternal, through <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt</hi> my Lord and Saviour, to whom with Thy Self, and Holy Spirit, be all Honour and Glory, now and for evermore, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A Prayer for Noon.</head>
                  <p>BLeſſed be Thy Name, O Lord my God, that Thou haſt preſerved me this Day hitherto. Bleſſed be Thy Name for all the Bleſſings which Thou haſt bee ſtowed upon me. Forgive me all the Sins which I have committed, and keep me the reſt of this Day from all evil. Grant O Lord,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:99817:53"/>that I may continue to ſerve Thee faithfully and truly this Day, and all the Days of my Life, that it may be well with me for ever and ever, thro' Jeſus Chriſt my Lord and Saviour, to whom with Thy ſelf and Holy Spirit be Glory and Honour, Power, Praiſe, and Thanksgiving, both now and for evermore; Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A Prayer for Night.</head>
                  <p>O Lord my God, I humbly and heartily bleſs and praiſe Thy Holy Name, for thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Preſervation of me this Day paſt; and for all the Bleſſings which Thou haſt beſtowed upon me. I bleſs Thee for my Health and Strength, Food and Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Peace and Safety, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all for my Redemption by Jeſus Chriſt, and my Hopes of Salvation by Him.</p>
                  <p>Forgive me, I beſeech Thee, all the Sins which either in
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:99817:54"/>Thought, Word, or Deed I have committed againſt Thee this Day. Forgive me that I have neglected any good which I might and ought to have done, or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently done it. I have forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Thee, O Lord, and I have done evil in Thy Sight. But I am heartily ſorry for all my Sins, and do earneſtly deſire, and ſeriouſly reſolve to ſerve Thee better for the Time to come. Remember not againſt me any of my paſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, but be in Chriſt fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled unto me. And give me Thy Grace, that I may hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth walk in thy Ways, and obey Thy Will in all Things.</p>
                  <p>Take me into Thy Tuition this following Night. Keep me when I cannot keep my ſelf. Keep me, O Lord, from all evil Thoughts, and hurtfull Luſts. Keep me from the Power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, the Prince of Darkneſs. Let Thy Holy Angels be my Guard, and thy mighty Power my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Defend me from all Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Diſquiets. <hi>Hide me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:99817:54"/>the Shadow of Thy Wings, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.8.</note> and keep me as the Apple of the Eye.</hi> When I am awake, let me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that Thine Eye is upon me;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.2.</note> and that <hi>Thou ſee'ſt my down-lying, and diſcerneſt my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Thoughts.</hi> Give me, O Lord, quiet Reſt and Sleep, and raiſe me up the next Day with renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Health and Strength to do Thee Service. Continue thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to me through all my Life, and in Death ſhew me thy Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>Bleſs and keep Thy whole Church, Continue Truth and Peace in this Land. Bleſs and preſerve my Parents in Life and Health. Let all my dear Friends and Relations be Happy in Thy Love and Favour.</p>
                  <p>Bleſs me, O Father, and ſave me for Thy Mercies ſake, in Chriſt Jeſus my Redeemer; To whom, with thy Self and Holy Spirit, be Honour, Glory, and Praiſe, for ever and ever, Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:99817:55"/>
               <head>Prayers for Servants.</head>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A Prayer for the Morning.</head>
                  <p>O Lord God, I heartily bleſs Thy Holy Name for kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping me this Night paſt in Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and raiſing me up with renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Health and Strength this Morning Hadſt Thou dealt with me, O Lord, according to my Deſerts, Thou might'ſt have ſent me into the Land of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and I might have made my Bed in Hell. But, O Lord, as Thou haſt mercifully kept me when I could not keep my ſelf, ſo take me, I beſeech Thee, into Thy Holy Tuition, and keep me henceforth from all Evil: Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don my Sin, and preſerve me to Thy everlaſting Kingdom.</p>
                  <p>Direct me, O God, and lead me forth in Thy Fear; and ſo bleſs and proſper me in all the Works and Buſineſſes of this day.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:99817:55"/>Grant that I may faithfully and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently diſcharge the Duties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of me, in the Place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Thy Providence hath ſet me. Keep me, O Lord, from all evil Thoughts, which may defile my Heart, and from all evil Words and Actions, whereby I may of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend Thee, and deprive my ſelf of Thy Bleſſing and Favour. Grant that I may ſo remember Thine All-ſeeing Eye, as to demean my ſelf always as in Thy Sight, ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying and endeavouring to pleaſe and honour Thee in all things, that at the laſt Day I may give up my Account with Joy.</p>
                  <p>Protect Thy whole Church by thy Power, and bleſs all Thy People with Peace. Bleſs this Land, and preſerve the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Bleſs this Houſe and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily wherein I live, with all Temporal and Spiritual Bleſſings. Bleſs, guide, and keep thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to whom Thou haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Care and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof. Give me Grace, O Lord, to look upon them as
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:99817:56"/>ſtanding in Thy ſtead to me, that by the Honour and Obedience which I yield to them according to Thy Command, I may ſerve and honour Thee; and, according to thy Promiſe, receive my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in Heaven. Grant, O Lord, that the Beauty and Goodneſs of Thy Government of Thy Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhould the Church may appear in their wiſe and good Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Houſe and Family committed to their Charge; that this Houſe may be to me, and all that live therein, as the Gate of Heaven, and Way to everlaſting Happineſs. Let thy Bleſſing, O Lord, crown all the Labours of thy Servants with good Succeſs, that whatſoever they do may proſper; and man may have Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſay. <hi>The Lord be mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified which hath Pleaſure in the Proſperity of His Servants.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.27.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Bleſs all my Friends and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and all that have been Inſtruments of Good to me: let all who have ſhew'd any Kindneſs to thy unworthy Servant, be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:99817:56"/>Happy in Thy Love and Favour.</p>
                  <p>Now, O Lord, be with me I beſeech Thee this Day, and bleſs me both in Body and Soul. Put Thy Fear into my Heart, that I may not ſin againſt Thee: Give me Health and Strength, that I may chearfully ſerve Thee. And when Thou haſt finiſhed Thy Will with me on Earth, fulfill my Deſire, O Lord, and make me perfectly happy with Thee in Heaven, thro' the Merits of my Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; To whom, with Thy Self and Holy Spirit, be Glory, Power, and Praiſe, now and for evermore; Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A Prayer for Night.</head>
                  <p>O Lord God, who art Great in Power and rich in Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>I</hi> Thy Poor Creature do here humbly caſt my ſelf down at Thy Footſtool, beſeeching Thee for
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:99817:57"/>the Lord Jeſus Chriſt's ſake, to forgive me all the Sins of the Day paſt, yea, all the Sins which <hi>I</hi> have ever committed againſt Thee. Forgive me, O Lord, all my looſe Thoughts, all my raſh Words, all my irregular Actions, whatſoever Thy pure Eye hath at any time ſeen amiſs in me, and be in Chriſt fully reconcil'd to me. For <hi>I</hi> confeſs my Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and am heartily ſorry for my Sins. Give me Grace, O Lord, for the time to come, to ſerve and honour Thee by a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Obedience. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10.</note> 
                     <hi>Put Thy Laws in my Mind, and write them in my Heart.</hi> That <hi>I</hi> may know and do Thy Commandments. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain me, O God, by Thy Grace from thoſe ſins to which <hi>I</hi> am moſt inclin'd, and keep me from thoſe Evils which <hi>I</hi> am moſt apt to commit. Help me to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Temptations, and make me wiſe to avoid all Occaſions of ſin. Seeing my life is but ſhort on Earth, Lord ſuffer me not to ſin my Soul into Hell.</p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:99817:57"/>
                  <p>Bleſs all thoſe <hi>I</hi> am bound to pray for; my Friends and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Fleſh. Do good to all that are good, and requite all thoſe who have done me Good: let all the Benefits I have received from them, be redoubled into their own Boſoms.</p>
                  <p>Bleſs this Houſe and Family wherein I live: Preſerve thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to whom Thou haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Care and Government of the Family, and all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to them in ſafety. Grant Lord, that I may ſo ſhew all good Fidelity to them, that I may find Favour with Thee, who alone canſt make me truly Happy for ever.</p>
                  <p>And now Bleſſed be thy Name O Lord, who haſt as well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the Night for Reſt as the Day for Labour. Keep me, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech Thee, this Night from all Evil. Give me that comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reſt and Refreſhment, which may fit me for the Duties of the following Day. And grant, Lord, that where after a few days I ſhall
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:99817:58"/>ſleep in the Duſt, my Soul may reſt with Thee in Glory, through the Merits of my Bleſſed Lord and Redeemer Jeſus Chriſt, to whom with Thee, O God the Father, and God the Holy Ghoſt be Glory and Majeſty, Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Power, and Praiſe, now and for evermore; Amen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If thou art weary and ſleepy, or not being able to Read, canſt not learn the foregoing Prayers by Heart, rather than lie down at Night like a Beaſt, and riſe up in the Morning, and go out to thy Work, without any ſerious Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of God; or pious Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of thy Dependance on Him,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 17.28.</note> in whom thou liveſt, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, and haſt thy Being, <hi>and without whoſe up-holding Hand thou canſt not ſubſiſt a Moment, without dropping into Duſt, and (if in thy Sins) into Hell, Kneel down on thy Knees, and ſay,</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:99817:58"/>
                  <head>At Night.</head>
                  <p>Bleſſed be Thy Name, O Lord God, who haſt kept me this Day paſt. Forgive me, I beſeech Thee, all my Sins, and keep me from Sin and Danger this Night, and raiſe me up, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſht with quiet Reſt and Sleep, to ſerve Thee better the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Day, to Thy Glory and my Salvation, thro' Jeſus Chriſt my onely Lord and Saviour; Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>In the Morning.</head>
                  <p>Bleſſed be thy Name, O Lord, who haſt kept me in Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and refreſht me with Reſt and Sleep this laſt Night. Now be with me, I beſeech thee, and keep me this Day from all Evil. Guide me in all my ways, and bleſs me in all my Works, and bring me in the end to everlaſting Life in Heaven, thro' Jeſus Chriſt, my Lord and Redeemer: Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:99817:59"/>
               <head>A Prayer for the Lord's Day.</head>
               <p>O Moſt Holy and Glorious Lord God, Thou art great in Thy Self, and yet good to man: Thou art gloriouſly exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted above the greateſt of Kings, and yet haſt a gracious Regard to the meaneſt of Thy Creatures. The Heavens, O Lord are the Work of thy Hands, and Thou haſt made the Earth, and all things therein Thou art great in Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Dreadfull in Majeſty, and glorious in Holineſs. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, what is man, that Thou remembreſt him? or the Son of man, that Thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeſt him? <note place="margin">
                        <hi>&amp;</hi> 39.5.</note> Verily every man at his beſt State is altogether Vanity.</hi> And yet how <hi>wonderfull are Thy Works, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>&amp;</hi> 107.8.</note> O God, which thou haſt wrought for the Children of men!</hi> For man thou haſt made the World, and repleniſht it with a rich Variety of Creatures, both for his Uſe and Delight. Thou haſt appointed all things to ſerve him, that he might with more
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:99817:59"/>chearfulneſs and Delight ſerve Thee. For man thou haſt ſent and ſlain Thine own Son; that guilty, loſt man, whom Thou mighteſt have juſtly thrown into everlaſting Darkneſs in Hell, might for ever live with Thee, in a Paradiſe of Divine Pleaſures, in a Heaven of Bliſs and Glory. O Lord, grant that I, thy poor Creature, may ſo love Thee and ſerve Thee here, that I may at length enjoy Thee fully, and praiſe Thee eternally in heaven.</p>
               <p>In Order to this End, I bleſs Thy Name, O Lord, that Thou haſt appointed a Day of Reſt from all worldly Labours, that I might attend upon Thee in the Duties of thy ſolemn Worſhip and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. O Lord, make this Day of reſt, to be to me a day of ſpiritual Refreſhment and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Delight. Grant that I may this Day hear the Voice of my Saviour calling to <hi>all that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and are heavy laden to come to</hi> Him, that he may give them <hi>Reſt;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28.</note> and make me ſo ſenſible of the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:99817:60"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:99817:60"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:99817:61"/>Burden of my Sins, that I may betake my ſelf to Him by a hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Repentance and lively Faith, and may obtain a Holy Reſt, in the Remiſſion of my ſins, and the ſalvation of my ſoul.</p>
               <p>Keep me this Day, O Lord, from Vanity and Idleneſs, from fooliſh-ſpeaking and evil-doing; and make me very diligent and ſerious in the Duties of Thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, that I may not let ſlip a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py opportunity of inſuring my ſalvation, nor miſpend that Time, which Thou vouchſafeſt me for the Good of my ſoul; but ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly employ it in the Duties of true Piety, for the getting and encreaſing of Knowledge and Grace, and treaſuring up for my ſelf Glory in Heaven.</p>
               <p>Keep me, O Lord, from all vain, worldly, and wanton Thoughts, which may take off my Minde from a ſerious Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Thy Word, and hinder me from joining with a Holy De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion in Thy worſhip: Grant that I may enter into Thy Houſe
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:99817:61"/>as into Heaven, and demean my ſelf there as in Thy ſight and Preſence; and Lord ſend me not away without Thy Bleſſing.</p>
               <p>Grant, O Lord, that <hi>to Day, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.13.18.</note> even while it is called to Day, I may hear Thy Voice</hi> Thy word, with a ſerious Reſolution to obey Thy will in all Things, leſt <hi>Thou ſwear in Thy Wrath, that I ſhall never enter into Thy Reſt.</hi> O let me not go from <hi>Thy Houſe, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.17.</note> the Gate of Heaven</hi> into everlaſting Darkneſs in Hell. But, Lord, ſpeak to Thy ſervant this day, thoſe words which may effectually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to my ſalvation. Grant, I humbly beſeech Thee, that I may ſo ſerve Thee this Day, and all the dayes of my Life, that in the End I may be truly Bleſſed for ever, through the Merits of my onely Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, to whom, with Thy ſelf and Holy Spirit, Be Glory and Honour, Dominion <hi>and Power, Thankſgiving and Praiſe, now and for evermore,</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:99817:62"/>
               <head>A Prayer before Reading the Holy Scriptures.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>OPen my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> O Lord, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.45. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.</note> that I may <hi>underſtand the Scriptures, which are able to make me wiſe to Salvation.</hi> Grant that I may ſo believe Thy word, as to do Thy will, and walk in that way, which will bring me in the end to Life eternal Eternal, through Jeſus Chriſt, my Lord and Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>A Prayer at the firſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the Church.</head>
               <p>LOrd, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.13.</note> 
                  <hi>be merciful to me a ſinner,</hi> and forgive me my ſins, that make me unworthy to come into Thy Holy Preſence. Aſſiſt me, O God, by Thy Grace, to the duties of thy Service. Grant that <hi>I may ſerve Thee acceptably,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28.</note>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:99817:62"/>with Reverence and Godly Fear.</hi> Oh ſend me not away without a Bleſſing. And as Thou haſt now brought me into Thy Houſe, in the End bring me to Heaven, through the Merits of Jeſus Chriſt, my Lord and Saviour; <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>At Departure from Church.</head>
                  <p>Forgive me, O Lord, all my wandring thoughts, and want of due ſeriouſneſs in thy holy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. O let not my infirmities hinder thy Acceptance, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive me of thy bleſſing.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.26.</note> 
                     <hi>Teach</hi> me, O Lord, by <hi>Thy Spirit</hi> what thou haſt taught me by thy word, and grant that I may ſo <hi>remember and do</hi> thy Will, that I may be <hi>Bleſſed in my Deed,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.25</note> and in my End Happy for ever, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, my Lord and Saviour; <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:99817:63"/>
               <head>A Confeſsion and Prayer to be uſed after Self-Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in Order to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of the Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</head>
               <p>O Lord <hi>my God,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ezr. 9.6.</note> I have juſt Cauſe to be <hi>aſham'd to lift up mine eyes</hi> to Heaven, or once to look up towards Thee, whom I have ſo grievouſly offended by my ſins. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.3 <hi>&amp;</hi> 51.5.</note> For, O Lord, <hi>I have gone aſtray from the Womb;</hi> yea, <hi>I was conceived and born in Sin, and brought forth in Iniquity.</hi> It might have been juſt with Thee to have ſnatcht me from the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of Mother, and caſt me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Belly of Hell. But, O Lord, Thou waſt pleaſed to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent me with the Gifts of Thy Grace, and Fruits of Thy Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. For before I was capable to know Thee, or to diſcern be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Good and Evil, Thou waſt pleaſed, by Thy Holy Baptiſm,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:99817:63"/>to admit me into Thy Houſe and Family, and to accept me for one of Thy Children. Thou waſt pleaſed to take me into a Holy Covenant with Thy ſelf, and to promiſe me the Kingdom of Heaven for mine Inheritance: and Thou haſt been very Good and Gracious to me from that Time to this very Day. But, O Lord my God, I have grievouſly ſinned againſt Thee, by too great a Complyance with the World, the Fleſh and the Devil, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to that mighty obligation which was laid upon me in my Baptiſm. I have not, O Lord, ſo ſtedfaſtly believed Thy Truth, and obeyed Thy Will, as lought, I have daily offended Thee by the Breach of Thy Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and have juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved Thy Wrath and Hell-Fire. <hi>I am no more worthy to be called Thy Son,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk</hi> 15.19.</note> or to be accounted one of Thy ſervants.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>O Lord,</hi> I am heartily ſorry for my ſins, and ſtedfaſtly purpoſed by Thy Grace to lead
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:99817:64"/>a New life. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.1</note> 
                  <hi>Be merciful unto me, O God, be merciful unto me,</hi> and pardon all my ſins, for thy Names ſake; and ſeal that Pardon to my ſoul, in the Blood of my Saviour. Thou haſt promiſed Pardon,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>O Lord,</hi> to the truly penitent; and to him that believeth in thy Son Jeſus Chriſt, life eternal. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, <hi>O Lord,</hi> I heartily repent of all my ſins, and ſtedfaſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, putting my whole Truſt in him alone for my Salvation. Behold, I give my ſelf up intirely to him, being deſirous to live to him, and willing to dye for him, rather than by denying his truth, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeying his Voice, to diſhonour him. For his ſake ſpeak Peace to my ſoul in the Pardon of my ſins and the Aſſurance of my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. And, <hi>O Lord,</hi> ſo renew me by thy Grace, and <hi>uphold me by Thy Spirit,</hi> that I may not relapſe into any of my former ſins, but continue to glorifie Thee by a holy Obedience all the days of my life.</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:99817:64"/>
               <p>Grant, O Lord, that I may <hi>love my Brethren,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22.</note> that bear thine Image <hi>with a pure heart fervent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;</hi> and that (whatſoever uſage I receive in the World) I may be in Charity with all men. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold O Lord, I heartily forgive all them, who at any time have done me wrong, and I beſeech thee to give them, that ſtill live in the guilt of their ſins, true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and a gracious pardon, that their Souls may be ſaved in the Day of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
               <p>Draw forth my Heart, O Lord, in hungring deſires after Chriſt, and ſatisfie my Soul as with Marrow and Fatneſs, with plentiful Communications of Grace from his fulneſs. Fit me, O Lord, for a Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him, and raiſe me to a nearer Conformity to him, in all his imitable excellencies, that I may at length be made like to him, and live with him in Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>Furniſh me, O Lord, with all thoſe Heavenly Graces, and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:99817:65"/>Holy Affections, which may make me meet to Feaſt with my Bleſſed Saviour in his Holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Therein ſeal up thine Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant of Grace to my Soul, Communicate to me the beneſits of my Saviour's Body and Blood, and refreſh me with the Holy comforts of thy Spirit. And grant that, all the reſt of my life, I may ſeriouſly endeavour to anſwer a renewed Obligation to Obedience, by a conſtant Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly care to keep all thy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Enable me, O God, by thy Grace to perſevere to the end, that I may be certainly Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for ever, through the merits of my Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, to whom with thy ſelf, and Holy Spirit, be all Honour and Glory, now and for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more; Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:99817:65"/>
               <head>A Prayer before Receiving of the Lord's Supper.</head>
               <p>GOod Lord, pardon my ſin, and ſeal that pardon this day to my Soul, in the Blood of my Saviour; Give me a lively Faith in him, that as I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Bread and Wine, I may partake of the ſaving bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of his Body and Blood, in his Holy Supper. Strengthen and refreſh my Soul, O God, with Spiritual Food, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve me both Body and Soul to Eternal Life, through Jeſus Chriſt my onely Lord and Saviour; Amen.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>At the receiving of the Bread, ſay with your ſelf.</head>
                  <p>O Lord, I heartily accept thy Son to be my Saviour; and as he gave his Body to be broken for me, I give my ſelf, Body and Soul to him for ever.</p>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:99817:66"/>
                  <p>O Bleſſed Jeſus, let me rather be broken in pieces, than ever do any thing which may diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thee, my Dear Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>At the Receiving of the Cup<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſay,</head>
                  <p>Now Lord, waſh away all my ſins in the Blood of my Saviour, and ſave my Soul for thy Mercies ſake.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Then having drunk of the Wine, ſay,</head>
                  <p>How ſweet is thy Love, O Dear Jeſus, who haſt ſhed thy Blood for my Salvation? O let me rather ſhed my deareſt Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blood for thee, than ever willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſin againſt thee.</p>
                  <p>Behold, Lord, I now give my ſelf up to thee, and thy ſervice: O let me ſee thy Salvation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:99817:66"/>
                  <head>Having Receiv'd, ſay with your ſelf,</head>
                  <p>Now, O Lord, thou art my God, and I am thine, both in Body and Soul, by a perpetual Covenant, ſealed with the Blood of my bleſſed Saviour. O let my ſoul be furniſhed with thy Grace, and fill'd with thy Spirit, that I may chearfully ſerve thee, while I live, and when I dye, fully enjoy thee for ever; Amen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>When you depart from the Lord's Table, labour to feel your Heart inflam'd with love to God and Chriſt, and fill'd with ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and joy in his Love to you, and to find your Soul fixed in a firm Reſolution of Holy Obedience to your Lives end. Take heed your heart do not entertain Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Thoughts, and that you do not open your ears, or looſe your tongue to Worldly Diſcourſe. But medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on the mercies of God to you
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:99817:67"/>in Chriſt, on the Promiſes and Priviledges of the Covenant of Grace, on the duties of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whereby you must glorifie God on Earth, and on the Glory and Bleſſedneſs reſerved for you in the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Being return'd home, retire your ſelf to give thanks to God for his Mercy in Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Thanksgiving after Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lord's Supper.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BLESS the LORD, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1.</note> O my Soul, and all that is within me, bleſs his Holy Name;</hi> who hath ſealed up to me this day the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of my ſins in the blood of my Saviour; who hath enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd me with Heavenly dainties at his Holy Table. Grant, O God, that in the ſtrength of this Spiritual Food, I may walk be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee in the wayes of a Holy obedience, till I ſhall at length attain to Eternal Bleſſedneſs, through my only Saviour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:99817:67"/>Jeſus Chriſt; Amen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As oft as thou receiveſt the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lord's Supper, be ſure to read thy Duty, as a Child or Servant, before declar'd, and the Rules of good Life here follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Grace before Meat.</head>
                  <p>Bleſs and Sanctifie thy good creatures to me, O my God, through Jeſus Chriſt; Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>After Meat.</head>
                  <p>Bleſſed be thy Name, O my God, for theſe, and all other thy good gifts, through Jeſus Chriſt; Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:99817:68"/>
               <head>In Company with others.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Before Meat.</head>
                  <p>God be merciful to us, and bleſs us, and give us a Sanctified uſe of theſe, and all other his Bleſſings, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord; Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>After Meat.</head>
                  <p>Bleſſed be God for theſe, and all his Bleſſings. Give us Grace, O Lord, to ſpend the ſtrength we receive from them in thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, to thy Glory, and our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord; Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:99817:68"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Chriſtian Converſation;</hi> IN <hi>Some neceſſary Cautions and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections to</hi> Young People <hi>for the Government of their Thoughts, Words and Actions: Or, RULES of Good LIFE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>HAve a great care of your Thoughts.</hi> Theſe are the ſprings of Action; Though the thoughts of mens heart are <hi>ſecret,</hi> and indiſcernible, they oſt become very <hi>viſible</hi> in their Lives. Words and Actions are but the <hi>Apparel of the Thoughts,</hi> Theſe appear upon the <hi>open Stage</hi> of the world, and proclaim what was before done in the <hi>ſecret Chambers</hi> of the Soul.</p>
            <p>Evil Thoughts are the <hi>ſeeds of ſin</hi> and vice, which not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd, will (as noxious weeds) overgrow the whole Life; Theſe
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:99817:69"/>
               <hi>little ſparks</hi> firſt kindle the fire of Luſt, and then of Hell.</p>
            <p>Know thoughts are not <hi>free;</hi> God's Law limits them: nor are they <hi>hidden;</hi> God's eye ſees them. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 139.2.</note> 
               <hi>Thou underſtandeſt my Thoughts afar off,</hi> ſaith <hi>David.</hi> Remember God's eye is upon your heart, and ſo do not har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour any evil thoughts. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.2.</note> 
               <hi>Be not forgetful</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain ſtrangers: for thereby ſome have entertain'd Angels un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares.</hi> Be careful ſay I, not to entertain evil thoughts: for ſo may you entertain the Devil un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares. The Devil by evil thoughts, inſinuates himſelf into the hearts of men, that he may corrupt their Lives, and deſtroy their Souls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vain Thoughts,</hi> though little regarded (as the <hi>ſwarms of Flies that corrupted the Land of Egypt</hi>) are very pernicious. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 8.24.</note>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>O Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>waſh thine heart from wickedneſs, that thou mayeſt be ſaved: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.113.</note> how long ſhall thy vain Thoughts lodge within
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:99817:69"/>thee?</hi> Ceaſe not then, till you can ſay with <hi>David, I hate vain Thoughts, but thy Law do I love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Keep a conſtant watch againſt all evil words.</hi> By evil thoughts you defile your own Soul, by evil words you may defile others alſo. The malignity of the heart is oft diffus'd by the tongue, to the infection of many: And therefore let <hi>David</hi>'s reſolution be yours; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.1.4.</note> 
               <hi>I ſaid I will take heed to my waies, that I ſin not with my Tongue.</hi> Remember the wiſe and Holy God hears all the words you ſpeak. <hi>There is not a word in my Tongue</hi> (ſaith Holy David) <hi>but lo, O LORD, thou knoweſt it altogether.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let your <hi>words be few</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.2.</note> and free from Folly. <hi>A fool's voice,</hi> (ſaith the wiſe man) <hi>is known by a multitude of words, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.27.</note> but he that hath knowledge ſpareth his words.</hi> Think before you ſpeak, ſilence is uſually ſafe: whereas raſh words oft recoile to the hurt of him that ſpake
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:99817:70"/>them. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.7.</note> However, <hi>in the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of dreames, and many words, there are alſo diverſe vanities: but fear thou God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Temperance of Tongue is a neceſſary virtue of true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; And therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.26.</note> 
               <hi>If any man among you, ſeem to be Religious; and bridleth not his Tongue, but deceiveth his own heart, this man's Religion is vain;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>c.</hi> 3.2.</note> But, <hi>If any man offend not in Word, the ſame is a perfect man, and able alſo to bridle the whole body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eſpecially take heed of all fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and impure ſpeeches; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how ſtrict a charge is given you in the Goſpel. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.29.</note> 
               <hi>Let no corrupt Communication come out of your Mouth, but that which is good to the uſe of edifying, that it may Miniſter Grace unto the Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. <note place="margin">31.</note> Let all clamour and evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeaking be put away from you.</hi> And as for <hi>Fornications, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 4.3.</note> and all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs or Covetouſneſs, let it not be once named amongſt you, as becometh Saints; <note place="margin">4.</note>Neither fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:99817:70"/>nor fooliſh talking, nor jeſting, which are not convenient: but rather giving of thanks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that your words may be Holy, keep the heart pure; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 12, 34, 35, 36, 37.</note> 
               <hi>For out of the abundance of the heart, the mouth ſpeaketh. A good man out of the good treaſure of his heart bringeth forth good things: and an evil man, out of the evil treaſure, bringeth forth evil things. But I ſay unto you</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>that every idle word that men ſhall ſpeak, they ſhall give an account thereof in the day of Judgment. For by thy words thou ſhalt be juſtified, and by thy words thou ſhalt be condemned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.163.</note> 
               <hi>Count it a great wickedneſs to tell a lye. I hate and abhor ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) but thy Law do I love.</hi> And he that loves God, and his Law, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.22.</note> muſt needs hate and abhor Lying; For <hi>Lying Lips are an abomination to the LORD: but they that deal tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are his delight.</hi> Yea, a Lyar is hated both of God and men: men hate him becauſe he ſeeks to
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:99817:71"/>deceive them, and God hates him, becauſe he plainly deſpiſes him, whom he knowes he cannot deceive.</p>
            <p>The ſin of Lying ſubjects men to puniſhment, both from God and men. The common puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment amongſt men is this, he that is known to have told a Lye, ſhall not be believed when he ſpeaks Truth. God for one Lye ſtruck <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira</hi> with ſudden death; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 5.1. — 10.</note> And yet the greateſt puniſhment of Lying remains in Hell; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15.</note> For <hi>whoſoever loveth or maketh a Lye, ſhall be ſhut out of</hi> the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.44.</note> Lying is the Devil's ſin, and ſubjects man to his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8.</note> For, <hi>All Lyars ſhall have their part in the Lake, which burneth with Fire and Brimſtone; which is the ſecond death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lye not to excuſe a Fault: What will it avail you to ſeem innocent before men, if you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come doubly guilty before God? To eſcape a rebuke from man, will you venture to incur the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:99817:71"/>wrath of God? What folly is it for one to avoid the pricking of a Pin, to run upon the point of a Sword? Though God do not puniſh the fault, are you ſure he will pardon the Lye? To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume is the way to periſh. Know God will not pardon it, except you repent; And what deſperate Folly is it for a man to do that, which he knowes before he ſhall either certainly repent, or muſt Eternally periſh.</p>
            <p>Lye not for gain; Its a woful gain which is acquired by the loſs of God's favour, and an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Soul.</p>
            <p>Lye not at all. He that tells a Lye ſtrikes at God, and ſtabs his own Soul. When Lying ſhall mourn in Hell, Truth ſhall fit triumphant in Heaven.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. <hi>Shun ſwearing and curſing as much as you do Hell and Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation;</hi> For if you become guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſin, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34 37.</note> how can you eſcape the puniſhment? <hi>Swear not at all</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>but let your Communication be yea, yea, nay,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:99817:72"/>nay; Yea,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>Above all things,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.12.</note> my Brethren ſwear not, neither by Heaven, neither by the Earth, neither by any other Oath: but let your yea be yea, and your nay, nay, leſt ye fall into condemnation;</hi> For moſt certain it is, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.7.</note> 
               <hi>God will not hold him guiltleſs that taketh his Name in vain.</hi> Curſe none of God's creatures, leaſt God curſe you; Its the Character of a wicked wretch, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.7.109.17.</note> 
               <hi>His mouth is full of curſing, as he loved curſing,</hi> (ſaith the Divine Prophet) <hi>ſo let it come unto him; as he delighted not in Bleſſing, ſo let it be far from him.</hi> How dreadful will the State of Swearers and Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers be, when Chriſt Jeſus the Judge of the world ſhall ſay to them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41.</note> 
               <hi>Depart from me ye curſed, into Everlaſting Fire, prepared for the Devil, and his Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let not your words then ſwell with the poyſon of Oaths or Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. He that ſhoots theſe impoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd arrowes up towards Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſhall at length find they will
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:99817:72"/>fall down on his own head.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſaw</hi> ſaith St. John, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.13.</note> 
               <hi>three un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Spirits like frogs, come out of the Mouth of the falſe Prophet.</hi> Surely an Oath or a Curſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the Mouth of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, is as monſtrous, as if you ſhould ſee a Toad coming out of the Mouth of a man. If the Spirit of God be in the heart, how can the Language of Hell fall from the lips?</p>
            <p n="5">V. <hi>Provoke not any to Anger, and be not your ſelf ſoon or long Angry.</hi> A man in Anger is as a Houſe on fire; If a fire be kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in a houſe, you ſhould endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to quench it: but when there is none, its a great wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to kindle it. He is a very miſchievous Fool, that ſets his own houſe on fire. When An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is join'd with deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, the houſe is ſet on <hi>fire of Hell.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.21.22.</note> Raſh Anger is a degree of <hi>Murder;</hi> And therefore though provoked by an injury, <hi>Be not haſty in thy Spirit to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.9.</note> for Anger reſteth in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of Eools.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:99817:73"/>
            <p>Anger in exceſs opens a door to the Devil; where ſome evil there, that is a juſt cauſe of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.26.</note> is done, <hi>Be ye Angry, and ſin not: let not the Sun go down upon your wrath, neither give place to the Devil.</hi> He that lies down to ſleep in his Anger, hath the Devil for his Bed-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
            <p>Conſider, there is none can ſo much provoke you to anger, as you daily provoke God. If he, who is ſo great, bear with you, how much more ought you to bear with others? If you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Fire-brand on earth, take heed leaſt God make you one in Hell. Know, nothing does bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter become a Chriſtian, than the meekneſs and gentleneſs of Chriſt. <hi>Put on therefore (as the Elect of God, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12.13.</note> Holy and Beloved) Bowels of mercies, kindneſs, humbleneſs of mind, meekneſs, long-ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; Forbearing one another, and forgiving one another, if any man have a quarrel againſt any: even as Chriſt forgave you, ſo alſo do ye.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:99817:73"/>
            <p n="6">VI. <hi>Flee youthful Luſts, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.22.</note> and endeavour to preſerve a chaſt mind in a pure Body.</hi> Defile not that Body with Luſt, which was waſht with Chriſt's Blood in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. Know your Body is the <hi>Temple of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated by Baptiſm to his Holy Service; Now, <note place="margin">3.17.</note> 
               <hi>if any man defile the Temple of God, him ſhall God deſtroy:</hi> Now the body of man is not left defil'd by fleſhly luſts, then the Temple of God by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing turn'd into a loathſome ſtie for filthy ſwine.</p>
            <p>As he therefore <hi>who hath call'd you</hi> to the Profeſſion of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity <hi>is Holy, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15.</note> ſo be ye Holy</hi> and pure, both in Body and Mind. <hi>For this is the will of God, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.3.4, 5, 7.</note> even your Sanctification, that ye ſhould abſtain from Fornication: that everyone of you ſhould know how to poſſeſs his Veſſel</hi> his [ <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.5.</note> Body the Veſſel of his Soul, and for his Food] <hi>in Sanctification and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, not in the Luſt of concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, even as the Gentiles which know not God: for God hath not
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:99817:74"/>call'd us unto <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If Saints, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.2.</note> ye are the <hi>Sons of God,</hi> the Brethren of Chriſt, and Heirs of Heaven. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.4.</note> And <hi>when Chriſt, who is our Life ſhall appear, then ſhall ye alſo appear with him in glory.</hi> Now; <hi>every man that hath this hope in him pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifieth himſelf,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> keepeth himſelf chaſt, <hi>even as he is,</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> chaſt and <hi>pure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The happineſs of ſuch chaſt and pure perſons in the preſence of God in Heaven, was repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to St. <hi>John</hi> in Viſion. <hi>I looked,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.1—5.</note> (ſaith he) <hi>and lo a Lamb</hi> [the Lord Jeſus Chriſt] <hi>ſtood on the Mount Sion, and with him an Hundred Fourty and Four Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, having his Fathers Name written in their Foreheads; And I heard a voice from Heaven, as the voice of many waters, and as the voice of a great Thunder: and I heard the voice of Harpers, harping upon their Harps: and they ſung as it were a new Song, before the Throne, and before the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:99817:74"/>four Beaſts, and the Elders,</hi> [the Angels and Saints in Heaven:] <hi>and no man could learn that Song, but the Hundred and Fourty and Four Thouſand, which were Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from the Earth. Theſe are they which were not defiled with women; for they are Virgins: theſe are they which follow the Lamb, which way ſoever he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: theſe were Redeemed from among men, being the firſt Fruits unto God; and to the Lamb; And in their mouth was found no guile: for they are without fault before the Throne of God.</hi> Now if you deſire to ſhare in the happineſs of this <hi>Virgins-Company</hi> in Heaven, you muſt endeavour to prefer an immaculate purity here on earth.</p>
            <p>To this end, keep a ſtrict guard upon your Senſes. Open not your ears to impure Speech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, nor ſuffer your eyes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold vanity; For <hi>whoſoever look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on a woman to luſt after her, hath committed Adultery with her already in his heart,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.28.</note> ſaith our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour; For the prevention
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:99817:75"/>of this danger ſaith Holy <hi>Job, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job.</hi> 31.1.</note> I made a Covenant with mine eyes; why then ſhould I think upon a Maid?</hi> Wanton looks, as flaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of Lightning, and wanton Thoughts, as ſparks of Fire, often kindle thoſe Flames of Luſt, wherein both the Body and Soul is offer'd up as a Holocauſt to Satan. And therefore ſaith our Saviour, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.29.</note> 
               <hi>if thy right eye offend thee, pluck it out, and caſt it from thee: for it is profitable for thee that one of thy Members ſhould periſh, and not that thy whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhould be cast into Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But eſpecially ſhun the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of a wanton woman, which is as a Murthereſs that lies in wait for the life of a man. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.13, — 18, — 21, 22, 23.</note> Such was the Harlot of which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, who <hi>caught the young man, and kiſt him, and with an impudent face ſaid unto him, come let us take our fill of love until the Morning, let us ſolace our ſelves with Loves. With her much fair Speech ſhe cauſed him to yield; with the flattering of her Lips ſhe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:99817:75"/>forced him; He goeth after her ſtraight way, as an Ox goeth to the ſlaughter, or as a Fool to the correction of the Stocks: Till a dart ſtrike through his Liver; as a Bird haſteth to the ſnare, and knoweth not that it is for his Life.</hi> Carefully ſhun therefore all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of falling into the company of ſuch a woman. Take the Counſel of <hi>Solomon; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.8. &amp; 7.27.</note> Remove thy way far from her, and come not nigh the door of her houſe; For, her houſe is the way to Hell, going down to the Chambers of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">VII. <hi>Shun Revelling and Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſs;</hi> Theſe are ſins ſo incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which oblige all that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it, to Temperance and Sobriety, that whoſoever gives himſelf up to Revelling and Drunkenneſs, does in effect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce his Chriſtianity; And he is certainly a deſperate wretch, who for a little ſenſual pleaſure, will quit all his hopes of Heaven, and ſell the joyes of Paradiſe. He that lives in theſe ſins, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:99817:76"/>in the common Road to Hell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſciviouſneſs, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.3.</note> Lusts, Exceſs of Wine, Revellings, Banquetings, and abominable Idolatries,</hi> were the ſins of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> before their Converſion to Chriſtianity. How unworthy is it of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, to ſtain the Glory of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Profeſſion with the guilt of the ſins and vices of Heathens.</p>
            <p>Chriſtians know there is a day appointed, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.31.</note> wherein they muſt give an account to God for the time they have ſpent in the world, and for all the Actions of their lives; <hi>And</hi> therefore ſaith our Saviour; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.34.</note> 
               <hi>Take heed to your ſelves, leaſt at any time your hearts be overcharged with Surfetting and Drunkenneſs, and cares of this Life, ſo that day come upon you unawares.</hi> Surfetting and drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſs breed diſeaſes in mens Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and ſhorten their Lives. The puniſhment is here linkt to the ſin; whereas Temperance and Sobriety are a fair and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant path to Heaven; by Surfetting
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:99817:76"/>and Drunkenneſs, men take the fouleſt way, that they may make the ſhorteſt journey to Hell.</p>
            <p>Drunkenneſs is a vile debaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to a man. No perſon, that has but the heart of a Man, would ſuffer himſelf to be ſo vilely abuſed and debaſed by another, as by Drunkenneſs he abuſes and debaſes himſelf. A Sober Servant is to be preferred before a drunken Son. A drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Servant is no better than a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Beaſt. In Drunkenneſs a man commits two or three ſins in one; For he at once abuſes God's Bleſſings, and his own Body, and diſhonours and wrongs any to whom he owes Service and Obedience, which, having transformed himſelf into a brute beaſt, a raging Bedlam, or a ſenſleſs ſtock, he is not capable to perform. How woful is it, that he, that is call'd to be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, ſhould ceaſe to be a man! And how juſt is it, that God ſhould cut him off in his ſin, and caſt him into Hell, who has made
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:99817:77"/>himſelf uncapable to anſwer the end of his Calling, as a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, yea, of his Being, as a man.</p>
            <p>Know, you were born in a Night of darkneſs, a ſtate of ignorance and ſin: but by inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution in the Myſteries of the Chriſtian Religion, you may perceive the dawning of a day of Light, a State of Knowledge and Salvation by Jeſus Chriſt. Let the Apoſtle's Exhortation then prevail with you for a ſuitable demeanour. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.12, 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>The night</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is far ſpent, the day is at hand: let us therefore caſt off the works of darkneſs, and let us put on the Armour of Light. Let us walk honeſtly as in the day, not in Rioting and Drunkenneſs, not in Chambering and Wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, not in Strife and Envying. But put ye on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and make not Proviſion for the Fleſh, to fulfil the Luſts thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">VIII. <hi>Avoid ill Company.</hi> The keeping of ill Company hath
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:99817:77"/>been the utter undoing of many Young men. For while they have been carried on hereby in an idle, licentious courſe of life, they have deſtroy'd themſelves Bodies and Souls for ever. He that once engages himſelf in that ſociety of ſinners, which is as the <hi>Corporation of Hell,</hi> ſhall hardly ever recover ſo much freedom and honour as to become a <hi>Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen of Heaven.</hi> Happy is the man then that carefully keeps himſelf from evil Company, yea, this is the man who is pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Bleſſed by an Oracle of God. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that walketh not in the Counſel of the ungodly, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.1.</note> nor ſtandeth in the way of ſinners, nor ſitteth in the ſeat of the ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</hi> And therefore <hi>David,</hi> to clear his Integrity, thus makes his Profeſſion; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>I have not ſate with vain perſons, neither will I go in with Diſſemblers. I have hated the Congregation of evil do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: and will not ſit with the wicked.</hi> But, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.63.</note> 
               <hi>I am a Companion of all them that fear thee, and of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:99817:78"/>them that keep thy Precepts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Man's a ſociable Creature, and mutual converſe is the delight and ſweetneſs of Humane Life. But then it greatly concerns us to make choice of good company. For, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.20.</note> 
               <hi>he that walketh with wiſe men ſhall be wiſe: but a Companion of fools ſhall be deſtroyed.</hi> If it be known that a man has the plague, or ſome infectious diſeaſe upon him, will not every man ſhun his ſociety? Sin is the diſeaſe of the Soul, not leſs infectious than the Plague. Should you not have more care of your Soul than of your Body? Is a Temporal Life in this World, to be preferr'd before Eternal Life in Heaven? Can you touch pitch, and not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil'd? familiarly and delightfully converſe with ſinners, and not contract the guilt of ſin? 'Tis impoſſible. Do you ſeriouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them for all their Oaths and Curſes, all their evil words and actions, all their vanities and vitious exceſſes? If ſo, their company will ſoon become un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:99817:78"/>to you, and yours to them. If not, know you go away guilty of all their ſins in the ſight of God. Oh! What a load of guilt do men carry home with them from ill Company? Now are not thine own ſins enough to damn thee? How then wilt thou hold up thy head at the Judgment Seat of Chriſt, when thou ſhalt be charg'd with all the horrible ſins of that Company, with which thou didſt delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully converſe? For he that keeps another Company in ſinning, heartens and hardens him in his ſins, and ſo at once promotes his and his own Damnation. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if thou ſaw'ſt the Wrath of God, and his Judgments hang over the heads of theſe ſinners, if thou ſaw'ſt thoſe Black Devils that ſtand at their Elbowes, to prompt them to wickedneſs, if thou ſaw'ſt the burning Lake which is kindled underneath, them, into which they are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to fall every ſtep they take, every ſin they commit, thou
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:99817:79"/>would'ſt be afraid to come into their Company, and no Gold ſhould ever bribe thee to become one of their Society?</p>
            <p>If thou art wiſe, and haſt any regard to thy own welfare; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>Have no fellowſhip with the unfruitful works of darkneſs, but rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them. For it is a ſhame even to ſpeak of thoſe things which are done of them in ſecret.</hi> Keep thy diſtance then from them, and bind thy ſelf with firm reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, altogether to refrain their Society. Hear the Counſel of the wiſeſt of men, <hi>Solomon,</hi> and know therein thou heareſt the voice of God; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>Enter not into the Path of the wicked, and go not in the way of evil men; avoid it, paſs not by it, turn from it, and paſs away.</hi> Obſerve here, the wiſe man repeats expreſſions of the ſame import, no leſs than ſix times, to engage thee to ſhun the Society of ſinners, as if he ſhould cry out aloud to thee, and ſay, fly, fly, fly, fly, fly, fly evil Company, if thou loveſt the life
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:99817:79"/>of thy Soul; or otherwiſe thou art a dead man, utterly undone for ever.</p>
            <p>Know for certain, ſuch as the Company is, in which thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteſt in this World, ſuch ſhall thy Company be hereafter, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Saints in Heaven, or the Damned in Hell.</p>
            <p>If thou knoweſt not where to have Society with good men, know its far better to remain ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary, and to hold converſe with God, wherein the Pious Soul aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cends to Heaven, than to be tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling on with a great deal of merry Company towards Hell.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. <hi>Be very ſerious and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in the Duties of God's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</hi> Know the ſervice of God, and the Salvation of your Souls, are your great work and buſineſs in this World, which you are to mind above all other things. And be ſure what you do in theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, you do with all your might. No man will endure a negligent and ſlothful ſervant, who is ſtill
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:99817:80"/>mindleſs and heedleſs in what he goes about. Trifling with God, in matters of Eternal Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, is utterly intolerable.</p>
            <p>Be very diligent in attendance on the ſolemn Worſhip and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, on the Lord's Dayes, and be conſtant in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the duties of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Prayers and Praiſes to God on your own daies alſo: but be ſure you ſerve God in both, with all humble Reverence, Holy Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſs, and hearty Devotion. God's Service is the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent employment, and you muſt alwaies attend it with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt earneſtneſs of Spirit. Stir up your ſelf to ſerve God with all your ſtrength: employ all the powers of your Soul in the duties of Religion.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.24 — 30. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.4.</note> 
               <hi>Jacob wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with God in Prayer,</hi> and ſo gain'd a Bleſſing. If you play the Hypocrite in your Prayers, you muſt expect nothing but the <hi>Portion of Hypocrites in Hell-fire.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.51.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:99817:80"/>
            <p>When you approach the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, remember he is that great and dreadful God, who is Glorious in Majeſty, and Infinite in Excellency, and ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to him with all poſſible Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and Humility. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28.</note> 
               <hi>Let us have Grace</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>whereby we may ſerve God accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably, with Reverence and Godly Fear. For our God is a conſuming fire.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.6.</note> And <hi>O come</hi> (ſaith the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt) <hi>let us worſhip and bow down: let us kneel before the LORD our Maker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How intolerable is the Pride and Arrogance of ſome Perſons in this duty of Prayer! The greateſt Subject of the Kingdom, if he have a requeſt to the King, preſents his Petition to him on the Knee. But you ſhall ſee a ſorry Servant to a Mortal man, that will not be perſwaded to bow his Knees to Almighty God, when he ſhould joyn with the Aſſembly in Publick Prayers. The rude Carriage of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the ſpecial preſence of the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:99817:81"/>All-Glorious God, plainly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers a profane and Atheiſtical Spirit. Such an one, though he be come to <hi>God's Houſe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.17.</note> which is the <hi>Gate of Heaven,</hi> ſits there upon the brink of Hell.</p>
            <p>'Tis a great inſtance of the Divine Patience, that ſuch a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is not ſmitten with death in the place where he ſits. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.1, 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dab and Abihu the Sons of Aaron,</hi> we know for a like preſumption, were both puniſhed with ſudden Death. For, ſaith the LORD, <hi>I will be Sanctifi'd in them that come nigh me, and before all the people I will be Glorifi'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore as you tender the Honour of God, and the good of your own Souls, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach Gods preſence with great Reverence and Humility, and ſerve him with great ſeriouſneſs and ſincerity of heart, in all the Duties of Religion.</p>
            <p n="10">X. <hi>Let all your Actions and Employments, your Labours and Delights, even your moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Recreations be ſeaſon'd with
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:99817:81"/>the Fear of God, and a ſerious Remembrance of Death and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Where ever you are, whatſoever you do, remember the Eye of God is upon you, and ſo demean your ſelf as in his ſight and preſence. For, <hi>His Eyes are upon all the wayes of the Sons of men, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.19.</note> to give to every one according to his wayes, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Fruit of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Remember the day is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when you muſt give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count before all the World, for whatſoever you have done in the Fleſh. Do nothing now, which you would be afraid or aſham'd to own then. When in the moſt ſecret place, you are tempted to any wicked deed, remember, though no man beholds you, the Eye of the great God is upon you, and ſo ſay with <hi>Joſeph; How can I do this great wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſin againſt God?</hi> Thus, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 39, 9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.41.</note> 
               <hi>ſtand in aw, and ſin not.</hi> Let the fear of God reſtrain you from whatſoever is evil; and let the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:99817:82"/>Love of God carry you on with Delight, to whatſoever is good.</p>
            <p>And though God do not deny you thoſe <hi>innocent Delights</hi> and Recreations, which are agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to your youthful years, and which may fit you for a more chearful diſcharge of your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective duties, yet you muſt be careful that thoſe very De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights be ſeaſon'd with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of God, and the day of Judgment. Mind, what the wiſe man ſayes to you, and what charge he gives you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this matter. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.9.</note> 
               <hi>Rejoyce, O Young man in thy Youth, and let thy heart chear thee in the dayes of thy Youth, and walk in the wayes of thy Heart, and in the ſight of thine Eyes: but know thou that, for all theſe things, God will bring thee into Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Know, thou art Mortal: and conſider that every Action thou doſt is a ſtep to Eternity, and every day thou liveſt, ſets thee a day nearer to thy death. And
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:99817:82"/>therefore live ſo now, as thou wilt wiſh thou hadſt done when thou comeſt to dye. The time of death is uncertain; But moſt certain it is, Chriſt Jeſus will ſhortly come to call every one that has been faithful in his fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, from Labour to Reſt, and Sorrow to Joy. Then happy ſhall he be who has been moſt ſerious in God's Service; His Reſt ſhall be ſweet, and his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Glorious. Make good uſe then of this inch of time, upon which depends the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eternity. Thy Glaſs is run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: be ſure thy work be done before the laſt ſand drop. Spend thy Life in God's Service, and in Death thou ſhalt ſee his Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Think ſtill, my Lord is at hand, and ſo be ever well-doing. <hi>Bleſſed is that ſervant, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.46, &amp;</note> whom his Lord when he comes ſhall find ſo doing.</hi> He will ſay to him, <hi>Well done good and faithful ſervant;
<note place="margin">25.21.</note> thou haſt been faithful in a little,</hi> take Poſſeſſion of much; <hi>Enter thou into the joy of thy Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:99817:83"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Now the God of all Grace, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.10.</note> who hath called us to his Eternal Glory by Chriſt Jeſus, make you perfect, ſtabliſh, ſtrengthen, and ſettle you; To him be Glory and Dominion for ever and ever. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt do well to repeat theſe Rules of Life (as alſo thy Duty before declar'd, as a Child or Servant) upon the Lords Day once a Month, for the better pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving them in Memory for thy direction in thy daily Practiſe. For certainly, the moſt of the ſins that men commit, to the diſhonour of God, and wounding of their own Conſcience, are committed through want of a preſent remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of their Duty, or a due conſideration of the mighty Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that lye upon them to do it. This great miſchief may be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily prevented by a frequent read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of theſe Rules of Life. Read therefore, and Remember, and do theſe things, that it may be well with thee for ever.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:99817:83"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Apples of Gold</hi> IN <hi>PICT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RES</hi> of <hi>SILVER,</hi> FOR <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and Delight of <hi>Children and Servants:</hi>
               </hi> BEING <hi>A Collection of certain Verſes, from ſome of our Divine Poems, more fit to be Imprinted on the Memories of Young People, than Prophane Songs.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The Preface.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOR the</hi> cloſe of your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, <hi>I here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you with a</hi> Delicate Diſh. <hi>'Tis</hi> choice Fruit, <hi>which
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:99817:84"/>grew in a</hi> Rich Soil. <hi>'Tis as the Fruit of</hi> Eden, <hi>that Tempted</hi> Eve, good for Food, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.6.</note> pleaſant to the Eyes, and deſirable to make one Wiſe. <hi>Only here is the difference; She could not eat of that without</hi> Sin <hi>againſt God, and</hi> Hurt <hi>to her ſelf: your eating of this may keep you from</hi> Sin, <hi>and prove the</hi> Health <hi>of your Soul. Freely feed then on this Fruit; 'tis not leſs whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome than pleaſant. 'Tis not as the Banquet of</hi> Midas <hi>or</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Plut. Mor.</note> Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, <hi>a</hi> Mock-Feaſt; <hi>'tis</hi> Gold <hi>for worth, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.11:</note> but</hi> Food <hi>for uſe.</hi> A Word fitly ſpoken (<hi>ſaith</hi> Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) is like Apples of Gold in Pictures of Silver. <hi>And</hi> inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in virtue, <hi>to Perſons in the</hi> Flower of their Age, is a word fitly ſpoken. <hi>Such are theſe pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Divine Poeſie, wherewith I here preſent you, Read, Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and Practiſe them: ſo ſhall you learn that</hi> Knowledge and Wiſdom, <hi>which is better than</hi> Silver and Gold; <hi>ſeeing it will at once make you</hi> Rich and Happy. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>For</hi> Wiſdom is a Tree of Life
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:99817:84"/>(<hi>ſaith</hi> Solomon) to them that lay hold upon her; and Happy is every one that retaineth her. <hi>And therefore,</hi> Receive my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, <hi>(ſaith He)</hi> and not Silver, and Knowledge rather than choice Gold. For Wiſdom is better than Rubies; and all the things that may be deſired are not to be compared to it. <hi>Here you have the</hi> Words of Wiſdom, <hi>which are</hi> Golden Apples, <hi>by the curious Art of Divine Poeſy, ſet in</hi> Silver Frames. <hi>Take and eat: for here you have both</hi> Food and Treaſure. <hi>What can you deſire more than what is here offer'd to your Acceptance? Accept and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, and you ſhall not fail at once, to find both</hi> Profit and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>And Profit with Delight com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin'd,</l>
                  <l>Is Meat and Muſick to the Mind.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb facs="tcp:99817:85"/>
               <head>The Names of the Authors, from whoſe Poems the following Verſes are Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>G. H.</hi> Mr. <hi>George Herbert</hi>'s Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Poems, called the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>R. C.</hi> Mr. <hi>Richard Craſhaw</hi>'s ſteps to the Temple.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>F. Q.</hi> Mr. <hi>Francis Quarles,</hi> his Emblems and Divine Fancies.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>J. D.</hi> Dr. <hi>Donne</hi>'s Poems.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>G.F.</hi> Mr. <hi>Giles Fletcher</hi>'s, Chriſt's Victory and Triumph.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>G. S.</hi> Mr. <hi>George Sandy's,</hi> his Paraphraſe of the Pſalms and Scripture Hymns:</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A. C.</hi> Mr. <hi>Abraham Cowley's</hi> Sacred Poems.</item>
                  <item>Some few others of leſs note, are ſignified by the firſt Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of their Names.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:99817:85"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Counſel to Young men.</hi> G. H.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THou, whoſe ſweet youth, and early hopes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hance</l>
                  <l>Thy rate and price, and mark thee for a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure;</l>
                  <l>Hearken unto a Verſer, who may chance</l>
                  <l>Rhyme thee to good, and make a bait of Pleaſure.</l>
                  <l>A Verſe may find him, who a Sermon flies,</l>
                  <l>And turn Delight into a Sacrifice,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Beware of Luſt: it doth pollute and foul</l>
                  <l>Whom God in Baptiſm waſht with his own Blood.</l>
                  <l>It blots the Leſſon written in thy Soul;</l>
                  <l>The Holy Lines cannot be underſtood.</l>
                  <l>How dare thoſe eyes upon a Bible look,</l>
                  <l>Much leſs towards God, whoſe Luſt is all their Book?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Drink not the third glaſs, which thou canſt nottame,</l>
                  <l>When once it is within thee; but before</l>
                  <l>Mayſt rule it, as thou liſt: and pour the ſhame,</l>
                  <l>Which it would pour on thee, upon the Floor.</l>
                  <l>It is moſt juſt to throw that on the ground,</l>
                  <l>Which would throw me there, if I keep the round.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He that is drunken, may his Mother kill</l>
                  <l>Big with his Siſter: he hath loſt the Reins,</l>
                  <l>Is out-law'd by himſelf: all kind of ill</l>
                  <l>Did with his Liquor ſlide into his Veins.</l>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:99817:86"/>
                  <l>The Drunkard forfeits man, and doth diveſt</l>
                  <l>All worldly Right ſave what he hath by Beaſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Take not his name, who made thy mouth, in yain:</l>
                  <l>It gets thee nothing, and hath no excuſe.</l>
                  <l>Luſt and Wine plead a pleaſure, Avarice gain:</l>
                  <l>But the cheap ſwearer through his open ſluce</l>
                  <l>Lets his Soul run for nought, as little fearing:</l>
                  <l>VVere I an <hi>Epicure,</hi> I could bate ſwearing.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVhen thou doſt tell anothers Jeſt, therein</l>
                  <l>Omit the Oaths, which true wit cannot need:</l>
                  <l>Pick out of Tales the Mirth, but not the ſin.</l>
                  <l>He pares his Apple, that will cleanly feed.</l>
                  <l>Play not away the virtue of that name,</l>
                  <l>VVhich is thy beſt Stake when griefs make thee tame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lie not; but let thy heart be true to God,</l>
                  <l>Thy mouth to it, thy actions to them both:</l>
                  <l>Cowards tell Lies, and thoſe that fear the Rod;</l>
                  <l>The ſtormy working Soul ſpits Lies and Froth.</l>
                  <l>Dare to be true. Nothing can need a Lye,</l>
                  <l>A fault, which needs it moſt, grows two thereby.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fly Idleneſs; which yet thou canſt not fly</l>
                  <l>By Dreſſing, Miſtreſſing and Complement.</l>
                  <l>If thoſe take up thy day, the Sun will cry</l>
                  <l>Againſt thee: for his light was only lent.</l>
                  <l>God gave thy Soul brave wings: put not thoſe feathers</l>
                  <l>Into a Bed, to ſleep out all ill weathers.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When thou doſt purpoſe ought (within thy power)</l>
                  <l>Be ſure to do it, though it be but ſmall.</l>
                  <l>Conſtancy knits the bones, and makes us ſtowre,</l>
                  <l>When wanton pleaſures becken us to thrall.</l>
                  <l>Who breaks his own Bond, forſeiteth himſelf:</l>
                  <l>What nature made a Ship, he makes a ſhelf.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:99817:86"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Do all things like a man, not ſneakingly:</l>
                  <l>Think the King ſees thee ſtill; for his King does.</l>
                  <l>Simpring is but a Lay-hypocriſie:</l>
                  <l>Give it a corner, and the Clew undoes:</l>
                  <l>VVho fears to do ill, ſets himſelf to taſk:</l>
                  <l>Who fears to do well ſure ſhould wear a Mask.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Look to thy Mouth: Diſeaſes enter there.</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt two Sconces, if thy Stomach call;</l>
                  <l>Carve, or diſcourſe, do not a Famine fear.</l>
                  <l>VVho carves is kind to two; who talks to all.</l>
                  <l>Look on Meat, think it dirt, then eat a bit;</l>
                  <l>And ſay with all; <hi>Earth to Earth</hi> I <hi>commit.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By all means uſe ſometimes to be alone.</l>
                  <l>Salute thy ſelf: ſee what thy ſoul doth wear.</l>
                  <l>Dare to look in thy Cheſt; for 'tis thine own:</l>
                  <l>And tumble up and down what thou findeſt there.</l>
                  <l>VVho cannot reſt till he good fellowes find,</l>
                  <l>He breaks up houſe, turns out of doors his mind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In Converſation boldneſs now bears ſway.</l>
                  <l>But know that nothing can ſo fooliſh be,</l>
                  <l>As empty boldneſs: therefore firſt aſſay</l>
                  <l>To ſtuff thy mind with ſolid bravery;</l>
                  <l>Then march on gallant: get ſubſtantial worth,</l>
                  <l>Boldneſs gilds finely, and will ſet it forth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Laugh not too much: the witty man laughs leaſt:</l>
                  <l>For wit is Newes only to Ignorance.</l>
                  <l>Leſs at thine own things laugh; leſt in the jeſt</l>
                  <l>Thy perſon ſhare, and the conceit advance.</l>
                  <l>Make not thy ſport abuſes: for the Fly</l>
                  <l>That feeds on Duug, is coloured thereby.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pick out of Mirth, like ſtones out of thy ground,</l>
                  <l>Profaneneſs, Filthyneſs, Abufiveneſs.</l>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:99817:87"/>
                  <l>Theſe are the ſcum, with which courſe wits abound:</l>
                  <l>The fine may ſpare theſe well, yet not go leſs.</l>
                  <l>All things are big with Jeſt: nothing that's plain</l>
                  <l>But may be witty, if thou haſt the vein.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Towards great perſons uſe reſpective boldneſs:</l>
                  <l>That temper gives them theirs, and yet doth take</l>
                  <l>Nothing from thine, in ſervice, care or coldneſs</l>
                  <l>Doth ratably thy Fortunes marr or make.</l>
                  <l>Feed no man in his ſins: for Adulation</l>
                  <l>Doth make thee parcel-Devil in Damnation.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Scorn no man's Love, though of a mean degree;</l>
                  <l>(Love is a Preſent for a Mighty King)</l>
                  <l>Much leſs make any one thine Enemy.</l>
                  <l>As Guns deſtroy, ſo may a little ſling.</l>
                  <l>The cunning workman never doth refuſe</l>
                  <l>The meaneſt tool, that he may chance to uſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Render to God his due, <hi>part of thy</hi> time:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Treaſure</hi> purloin'd cankers the whole Eſtate.</l>
                  <l>Sundays obſerve: think, when the Bells do chime,</l>
                  <l>'Tis Angels Muſick; therefore come not late.</l>
                  <l>God then deals Bleſſings: If a King did ſo,</l>
                  <l>VVho would not haſt, nay give, to ſee the ſhow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let vain or buſie thoughts have there no part:</l>
                  <l>Bring not thy Plough, thy Plots, thy Pleaſures thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</l>
                  <l>Chriſt purg'd his Temple, ſo muſt thou thy heart.</l>
                  <l>All worldly thoughts are but thieves met together</l>
                  <l>To cozen thee. Look to thy Actions well:</l>
                  <l>For Churches are either our Heav'n or Hell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Judge not the Preacher; for he is thy Judge:</l>
                  <l>If thou miſlike him, thou conceiv'ſt him not.</l>
                  <l>God calleth Preaching Folly. Do not grudge</l>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:99817:87"/>
                  <l>To pick out treaſures from an Earthen pot.</l>
                  <l>The worſt ſpeak ſomething good: if all want Senſe,</l>
                  <l>God takes a Text, and Preacheth Patience.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He that gets Patience, and the Bleſſing which</l>
                  <l>Preachers conclude with, hath not loſt his pains.</l>
                  <l>He that by being at Church eſcapes the ditch,</l>
                  <l>Which he might fall in by Companions, gains.</l>
                  <l>He that loves God's abode, and to combine</l>
                  <l>With Saints on Earth, ſhall one day with them ſhine.</l>
                  <l>In brief, acquit thee bravely, play the man.</l>
                  <l>Look not on pleaſures as they come, but go.</l>
                  <l>Defer not the leaſt virtue: life's poor ſpan.</l>
                  <l>Make not an Ell, by trifling in thy wo.</l>
                  <l>If thou do ill, the Joy fades, not the pains:</l>
                  <l>If well, the pain doth fade, the joy remains.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Confeſſion. G.S. in Pſal.</hi> 51.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LORD, to a ſinner Mercy ſhow:</l>
                  <l>Which ſince in thee ſo infinite;</l>
                  <l>Let all thy ſtreames of Mercy flow,</l>
                  <l>And purifie me in thy ſight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My ſins unmaſkt, before thee lye;</l>
                  <l>Who have deſerv'd thy wrath alone:</l>
                  <l>VVhich I confeſs, to teſtifie</l>
                  <l>Thy truth, and make thy Juſtice known.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In ſin conceiv'd, brought forth in ſin;</l>
                  <l>Sin ſuckt I from my Mothers Breaſt:</l>
                  <l>Thou lov'ſt a heart ſincere within,</l>
                  <l>VVhere wiſdom is a conſtant gueſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:99817:88"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Blot out my crimes; O ſcparate</l>
                  <l>My trembling guilt far from thy view!</l>
                  <l>A clean Heart in my Breaſt Create;</l>
                  <l>A Mind, to thee confirm'd, renew.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nor caſt me from thy Preſence, Lord;</l>
                  <l>Nor, O! Thy Holy Spirit withdraw:</l>
                  <l>But thy Life-quickning Grace afford;</l>
                  <l>Inlarge my will, t' embrace thy Law.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Reſolution.</hi> G. S. <hi>in Pſal.</hi> 119.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>YOung man thine Actions by God's Precepts guide:</l>
                  <l>From theſe let not thy zealous ſervant ſlide.</l>
                  <l>Thy word, writ in my heart, ſhall curb my will.</l>
                  <l>Lord, teach me how I may thy laws fulfil.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe by thy tongue pronounc't I will unfold.</l>
                  <l>Thy Teſtaments by me more priz'd than Gold.</l>
                  <l>On theſe I meditate, admire; there ſet</l>
                  <l>My Souls delight: theſe never will forget.</l>
                  <l>O let me live, t'obſerve thy laws: mine eyes</l>
                  <l>Illuminate to view thoſe Myſteries.</l>
                  <l>Me, a poor Pilgrim, with thy truth inſpire:</l>
                  <l>For which my Soul even fainteth with deſire.</l>
                  <l>The proud is curſt, who from thy Precepts ſtraies,</l>
                  <l>Bleſs and preſerve my ſoul, which them obeyes.</l>
                  <l>No hate of Princes from thy law deters:</l>
                  <l>My Study, my Delight, my Counſellers.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:99817:88"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Bible.</hi> A. C.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>THis</hi> Holy Book, like <hi>Heaven it ſelf,</hi> doth ſhine,</l>
                  <l>VVith thouſand lights of truth Divine.</l>
                  <l>So numberleſs the Stars, that <hi>well they may</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To Heaven's Gate make a Milky way.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet reaſon muſt aſſiſt too; for in Seas</l>
                  <l>So vaſt and dangerous as theſe,</l>
                  <l>Our courſe by Stars above we cannot know,</l>
                  <l>VVithout the compaſs too below.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tho <hi>Reaſon</hi> cannot through <hi>Faith's Mysteries</hi> ſee,</l>
                  <l>It ſees that there, and ſuch they be;</l>
                  <l>Leads to <hi>Heav'n's Door,</hi> and there does humbly keep</l>
                  <l>And there through chinks and key-holes peep.</l>
                  <l>Though it like <hi>Moſes,</hi> by a ſad command,</l>
                  <l>Muſt not come into th' <hi>Holy Land;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet thither it infallibly does guide,</l>
                  <l>And from a far 'tis all deſcry'd.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Charms and Knots.</hi> G. H.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who read a Chapter when they riſe,</l>
                  <l>Shall ne're be troubled with ill eyes.</l>
                  <l>A poor man's Rod, when thou doſt ride,</l>
                  <l>Is both a weapon and a guide.</l>
                  <l>VVho ſhuts his hand hath loſt his Gòld:</l>
                  <l>Who opens it, hath it twice told.</l>
                  <l>VVho goes to Bed, and doth not pray,</l>
                  <l>Maketh two nights to ev'ry day.</l>
                  <l>VVho by aſperſions throw a ſtone</l>
                  <l>At th' head of others, hit their own.</l>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:99817:89"/>
                  <l>VVho looks on ground with humble eyes,</l>
                  <l>Finds himſelf there, and ſeeks to riſe.</l>
                  <l>VVhen th' hair is ſweet, through Pride or luſt,</l>
                  <l>The Powder doth forget the duſt.</l>
                  <l>Take one from ten, and what remains?</l>
                  <l>Ten ſtill, if Sermons go for gains.</l>
                  <l>In ſhallow waters Heaven doth ſhow:</l>
                  <l>But who drinks on, to Hell may go.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>God's Greatneſs.</hi> G. S. in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>GOD our ſecret thoughts diſplayes;</l>
                  <l>All our works his balance weighs;</l>
                  <l>Giants bows his Forces break;</l>
                  <l>He with ſtrength inveſts the weak.</l>
                  <l>Who were full, now ſerve for bread;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe who ſerv'd, infranchiſed.</l>
                  <l>Barren wombs with children flow;</l>
                  <l>Fruitful Mothers Childleſs grow.</l>
                  <l>God frail man of life deprives:</l>
                  <l>Thoſe who ſleep in death revives:</l>
                  <l>Leads us to our filent Tombs;</l>
                  <l>Brings us from thoſe horrid Rooms:</l>
                  <l>Riches ſends, ſends Poverty:</l>
                  <l>Caſteth down, lifts up on high.</l>
                  <l>He from the deſpiſed duſt,</l>
                  <l>From the dunghil takes the juſt;</l>
                  <l>To the height of honour brings;</l>
                  <l>Plants them in the Thrones of Kings.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Man's Meanneſs.</hi> G. S. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LORD, how illuſtrious is thy Name!</l>
                  <l>Whoſe power both Heav'n and Earth proclaim!</l>
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:99817:89"/>
                  <l>Thy Glory thou haſt ſet on high,</l>
                  <l>Above the Marble-arched Sky.</l>
                  <l>The wonders of thy power thou haſt</l>
                  <l>In mouths of Babes, and Sucklings plac't;</l>
                  <l>That ſo thou might'ſt thy Foes confound,</l>
                  <l>And who in Malice moſt abound,</l>
                  <l>When I pure Heaven, thy Fabrick ſee,</l>
                  <l>The Moon and Stars diſpos'd by thee;</l>
                  <l>O what is man, or his frail Race,</l>
                  <l>That thou ſhould'ſt ſuch a ſhadow Grace!</l>
                  <l>Next to thy Angels moſt renown'd,</l>
                  <l>With Majeſty and Glory Crown'd;</l>
                  <l>The King of all thy Oreatures made;</l>
                  <l>That all beneath his feet haſt laid:</l>
                  <l>And that on Dales or Mountains feed;</l>
                  <l>That ſhady woods or deſerts breed;</l>
                  <l>What in the Aery Region glide,</l>
                  <l>Or through the rowling Ocean ſlide.</l>
                  <l>Lord, how illuſtrious is thy Name,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Pow'r both Heav'n and Earth proclaim!</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Humility.</hi> G. S. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 131.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THou Lord, my witneſs art:</l>
                  <l>I am not proud of heart;</l>
                  <l>Nor look with lofty eyes;</l>
                  <l>Nor envy, nor deſpiſe;</l>
                  <l>Nor to vain pomp apply</l>
                  <l>My thoughts, nor ſoar too high:</l>
                  <l>But in behaviour mild;</l>
                  <l>And as a tender child,</l>
                  <l>Wean'd from his Mothers Breaſt</l>
                  <l>On thee alone I reſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:99817:90"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The word of God.</hi> G. S. in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>GOd's laws are perfect, and reſtore</l>
                  <l>The Soul to life, even dead before.</l>
                  <l>His Teſtimonies, firmly true,</l>
                  <l>With wiſdom ſimple men indue.</l>
                  <l>The Lord's Commandments are upright,</l>
                  <l>And feaſt the Soul with ſweet delight.</l>
                  <l>His Precepts are all purity,</l>
                  <l>Such as illuminate the eye.</l>
                  <l>The fear of God, ſoil'd with no ſtain,</l>
                  <l>Shall Everlaſtingly remain.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s Judgments are Divine,</l>
                  <l>With Judgment he doth Juſtice join.</l>
                  <l>Which men ſhould more than Gold deſire,</l>
                  <l>Than heaps of Gold refin'd by fire:</l>
                  <l>More ſweet than honey of the Hive,</l>
                  <l>Or Cels, where Bees their treaſure ſtive.</l>
                  <l>Thy ſervant is inform'd from thence,</l>
                  <l>They their obſervers recompence.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>The World.</hi> F. Q.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>O VVhat a Crocodilian world is this,</l>
                  <l>Compos'd of treacheries and imnaring wiles!</l>
                  <l>She cloaths deſtruction in a formal kiſs,</l>
                  <l>And lodges death in her deceitful ſmiles;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She hugs the Soul ſhe hates, and there does prove,</l>
                  <l>The veryeſt tyrant, where ſhe vowes to love:</l>
                  <l>And is a Serpent moſt, when moſt ſhe ſeems a Dove:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thrice happy he, whoſe nobler thoughts deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>To make an object of ſo eaſie gains;</l>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:99817:90"/>
                  <l>Thrice happy he, who ſcorns ſo poor a prize</l>
                  <l>Should be the Crown of his heroick pains;</l>
                  <l>Thrice happy he that ne'er was born to try,</l>
                  <l>Her frowns or ſmiles, or being born did lye</l>
                  <l>In his ſad Nurſes Arms an hour or two, and dye.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Quip.</hi> G. H.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>The merry world did on a day,</l>
                  <l>VVith his Train-bands and Mates agree</l>
                  <l>To meet together where I lay,</l>
                  <l>And all in ſport to jeer at me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Firſt, Beauty crept into a Roſe,</l>
                  <l>VVhich when I pluckt not, Sir ſaid ſhe,</l>
                  <l>Tell me I pray, whoſe hands are thoſe?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But thou ſhalt anſwer, Lord, for me.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then Money came, and chinking ſtill,</l>
                  <l>VVhat tune is this, poor man? ſaid he;</l>
                  <l>I heard in Muſick you had ſkill;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But thou ſhalt anſwer, Lord for me.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then came brave Glory puffing by,</l>
                  <l>In Silks that whiſtled, who but he?</l>
                  <l>He ſcarce allow'd me half an eye.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But thou ſhalt anſwer, Lord, for me.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then came quick wit and Converſation,</l>
                  <l>And he would needs a comfort be,</l>
                  <l>And to be ſhort, make an Oration.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But thou ſhalt anſwer, Lord, for me.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet when the hour of thy deſign,</l>
                  <l>To anſwer theſe fine things ſhall come;</l>
                  <l>Speak not at large, ſay, I am thine:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And then they have their Anſwer home.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:99817:91"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Reſt.</hi> F. Q.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>How is the anxious Soul of man befool'd</l>
                  <l>In his deſire,</l>
                  <l>That thinks a Hectick Fever may be cool'd</l>
                  <l>In flames of Fire;</l>
                  <l>Or hopes to rake full heaps of burniſht Gold</l>
                  <l>From naſty Mire!</l>
                  <l>A whining Lover may as well requeſt</l>
                  <l>A ſcornful Breaſt,</l>
                  <l>To melt in gentle tears, as woe the world for reſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVhoſe Gold is double with a careful hand,</l>
                  <l>His cares are double;</l>
                  <l>The Pleaſure, Honour, VVealth of Sea and Land</l>
                  <l>Bring but a trouble;</l>
                  <l>The world it ſelf, and all the world's command</l>
                  <l>Is but a bubble:</l>
                  <l>The ſtrong deſires of man's inſatiate breaſt</l>
                  <l>May ſtand poſſeſt</l>
                  <l>Of all that earth can give, but earth can give no reſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The world's a ſeeming Paradiſe, but her own</l>
                  <l>And man's Tormenter;</l>
                  <l>Appearing fixt, but yet a rowling-ſtone:</l>
                  <l>VVithout a tenter</l>
                  <l>It is a vaſt circumference, where none</l>
                  <l>Can find a Centre:</l>
                  <l>Of more than earth can earth make none poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt;</l>
                  <l>And he that leaſt</l>
                  <l>Regards this reſtleſs world, ſhall in this world find reſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Retreat, Return.</hi> F. Q.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lord, when we leave the world, and come to thee,</l>
                  <l>How dull, how ſlug are we!</l>
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:99817:91"/>
                  <l>But when at earth we dart our wing'd deſire,</l>
                  <l>VVe burn, we burn like Fire.</l>
                  <l>If pleaſure becken with her balmy hand,</l>
                  <l>Her beck's a ſtrong command.</l>
                  <l>If honour call us with her Courtly breath,</l>
                  <l>An hours delay is death.</l>
                  <l>If Profits Golden finger'd-charms inveigle's,</l>
                  <l>VVe clip more ſwift than Eagles.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lord, ſtop our Flight, and turn our Courſe, that we</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>May fly as faſt to thee.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sunday.</hi> G. H.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>O day moſt calm, moſt bright;</l>
                  <l>The Fruit of this, the next world's Bud;</l>
                  <l>Th' Indorſment of ſupreme delight,</l>
                  <l>VVrit by a Friend, and with his Blood;</l>
                  <l>The Couch of time, cares Balm and Bay;</l>
                  <l>The week were dark but for thy light:</l>
                  <l>Thy torch doth ſhow the way.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The other dayes, and thou</l>
                  <l>Make up one man, whoſe face thou art,</l>
                  <l>Knocking at Heaven with thy brow:</l>
                  <l>The worky dayes are the back part;</l>
                  <l>The burden of the week lies there,</l>
                  <l>Making the whole to ſtoop and bow</l>
                  <l>Till thy releaſe appear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Man had ſtraight forward gone</l>
                  <l>To endleſs death: but thou doſt pull</l>
                  <l>And turn us round to look on one,</l>
                  <l>VVhom, if we were not very dull</l>
                  <l>VVe could not chooſe but look on ſtill;</l>
                  <l>Since there is no place ſo alone,</l>
                  <l>The which he doth not fill.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:99817:92"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sundayes the Pillars are,</l>
                  <l>On which Heaven's Palace arched lies:</l>
                  <l>The other dayes fill up the ſpare</l>
                  <l>And hollow room with vanities.</l>
                  <l>They are the fruitful Beds and Borders</l>
                  <l>In God's rich Garden: that is bare</l>
                  <l>VVhich parts their ranks and orders<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Sundayes of man's Life</l>
                  <l>Threaded together, on time's ſtring,</l>
                  <l>Make bracelets to adorn the wife,</l>
                  <l>Of the Eternal Glorious King.</l>
                  <l>On Sunday Heaven's Gate ſtands ope;</l>
                  <l>Bleſſings are plentiful and rife,</l>
                  <l>More plentiful than hope.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This day my Saviour roſe,</l>
                  <l>And did incloſe this Light for his:</l>
                  <l>That as each Beaſt his Manger knowes,</l>
                  <l>Man might not of his Fodder miſs.</l>
                  <l>Chriſt hath took in this piece of ground;</l>
                  <l>And made a Garden there for thoſe</l>
                  <l>VVho want Herbs for their wound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Reſt of our Creation</l>
                  <l>Our great Redeemer did remove</l>
                  <l>VVith the ſame ſhake, which at his Paſſion</l>
                  <l>Did earth, and all things with it move.</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Sampſon</hi> bore the doors away,</l>
                  <l>Chriſt's hands though nailed, wrought our Salvation,</l>
                  <l>And did unhinge that day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The brightneſs of that day</l>
                  <l>VVe ſullied by our foul offence:</l>
                  <l>VVherefore that Robe we caſt away,</l>
                  <l>Having a new at his expence,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe Drops of Blood paid the full price,</l>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:99817:92"/>
                  <l>That was required to make us gay,</l>
                  <l>And fit for Paradiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou art a day of Mirth:</l>
                  <l>And where the week dayes trail on ground,</l>
                  <l>Thy Flight is higher as thy Birth.</l>
                  <l>O let me take thee at the bound,</l>
                  <l>Leaping with thee from ſeven to ſeven,</l>
                  <l>Till that we both, being toſs'd from Earth,</l>
                  <l>Fly hand in hand to Heaven.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Church.</hi> G. S. in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>O how amiable are</l>
                  <l>Thy abodes, great God of war!</l>
                  <l>Happy men who ſpend their dayes</l>
                  <l>In thy Courts, there ſing thy praiſe.</l>
                  <l>Happy, who on thee depend;</l>
                  <l>Thine their way, and thou their end.</l>
                  <l>One day in thy Courts alone,</l>
                  <l>Far exceeds a Million.</l>
                  <l>In thy houſe contemn'd and poor,</l>
                  <l>I had rather keep a door,</l>
                  <l>Than with wicked men poſſeſs,</l>
                  <l>All that they call happineſs.</l>
                  <l>O thou Shield of our defence!</l>
                  <l>O thou Sun, whoſe influence</l>
                  <l>Sweetly glides into our hearts!</l>
                  <l>Thou, who all to thine imparts!</l>
                  <l>Happy! O thrice happy he,</l>
                  <l>VVho alone depends on thee.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Young Man's Mirth.</hi> F. Q.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.9.</note> 
                     <hi>Young man Rejoyce:</hi> what jolly mirth is here!</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let thy heart chear thee:</hi> what delicious chear!</l>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:99817:93"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In thy Young dayes:</hi> thy cares will reliſh ſweeter.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Walk thy own wayes:</hi> thy cares will paſs the fleeter.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pleaſe thine own heart:</hi> carve where it likes thee beſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Delight thine Eyes:</hi> and be a joyful Gueſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But know withall, the day will come, whereon</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thy Judge will doom thee for the deeds th'haſt done.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O what a Feaſt! O what a reckoning's here!</l>
                  <l>Thy cates are ſweet; the ſhot's extreamly dear.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Grace.</hi> G. H.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>My Stock lies dead, and no increaſe</l>
                  <l>Doth my dull Husbandry improve:</l>
                  <l>O let thy Graces without ceaſe</l>
                  <l>Drop from above.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If ſtill the Sun ſhould hide his Face,</l>
                  <l>Thy houſe would but a Dungeon prove,</l>
                  <l>Thy works nights Captives; O let Grace</l>
                  <l>Drop from above.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Dew doth every Morning fall;</l>
                  <l>And ſhall the Dew out-ſtrip thy Dove?</l>
                  <l>The Dew, for which Graſs cannot call,</l>
                  <l>Drop from above.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Death is ſtill working like a Mole,</l>
                  <l>And digs my Grave at each remove:</l>
                  <l>Let Grace work too, and on my Soul</l>
                  <l>Drop from above.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sin is ſtill hammering my heart</l>
                  <l>Unto a hardneſs, vold of love:</l>
                  <l>Let ſuppling Grace, to croſs his Art,</l>
                  <l>Drop from above.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:99817:93"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>O come! for thou doſt know the way:</l>
                  <l>Or if to me thou wilt not move,</l>
                  <l>Remove me where I need not ſay,</l>
                  <l>Drop from above.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Contentment.</hi> R. S.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I dwell in Grace's Court,</l>
                  <l>Enricht with Virtue's rights:</l>
                  <l>Faith guides my wit, Love leads my will;</l>
                  <l>Hope all my mind's delights.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In lowly vales I mount</l>
                  <l>To pleaſure's higheſt pitch:</l>
                  <l>My honeſt meanneſs Honour brings,</l>
                  <l>My poor Eſtate is rich.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My Conſcience is my Crown,</l>
                  <l>Contented thoughts my reſt.</l>
                  <l>My heart is happy in it ſelf;</l>
                  <l>My Bliſs is in my Breaſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Enough, I reckon wealth;</l>
                  <l>A mean, the ſureſt Lot;</l>
                  <l>That lies too high for baſe contempt,</l>
                  <l>Too low for envies ſhot.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My wiſhes are but few;</l>
                  <l>All eaſie to fulfil:</l>
                  <l>I make the limits of my power,</l>
                  <l>The bounds unto my will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I feel no care of Coin;</l>
                  <l>VVell-doing is my wealth:</l>
                  <l>My mind to me an Empire is,</l>
                  <l>VVhile Grace affordeth health.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Proſperity.</hi> F. Q.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Take heed, thou proſperous ſinner, how thou liv'ſt</l>
                  <l>In ſin, and thriv'ſt.</l>
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:99817:94"/>
                  <l>Thou that doſt flouriſh in thy heaps of Gold,</l>
                  <l>And Sums untold.</l>
                  <l>Thou, that hadſt never reaſon to complain</l>
                  <l>Of Croſs or Pain:</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe unafflicted Conſcience never found</l>
                  <l>Nor check, nor wound.</l>
                  <l>Believe it, <hi>Proſper,</hi> thy deceitful leaſe</l>
                  <l>Affords thee neither wealth, nor joy, nor peace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy Golden heaps are nothing but the price</l>
                  <l>Of Paradiſe:</l>
                  <l>Thy flatt'ring pleaſures, and thy aery joyes,</l>
                  <l>But painted toyes:</l>
                  <l>Thy peaceful Conſcience is but like a dog,</l>
                  <l>Ty'd in a clog.</l>
                  <l>Believe it, <hi>Proſper</hi> thy deceitful Leaſe</l>
                  <l>Allows thee neither wealth, nor joy, nor peace.</l>
                  <l>Thy heaps of Gold will ſtand thee in no ſteed.</l>
                  <l>At greateſt need:</l>
                  <l>Thy empty pleaſure will convert thy laughter</l>
                  <l>To groans hereafter.</l>
                  <l>Thy ſilent Conſcience when inlarg'd, will roar,</l>
                  <l>And rage the more.</l>
                  <l>Believe it, <hi>Proſper</hi> thy deceitful leaſe</l>
                  <l>Affords thee neither wealth, nor joy, nor peace.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Paradiſe.</hi> G. H.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I bleſs thee Lord, becauſe I <hi>GROW</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Among thy trees, which in a <hi>ROW,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To thee both Fruit and Order <hi>OW.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What open Force, or hidden <hi>CHARM</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Can blaſt my Fruit, or bring me <hi>HARM,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>While the incloſure is thine <hi>ARM.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Incloſe me ſtill for fear I <hi>START,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be to me rather ſharp and <hi>TART</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then let me want thy hand and <hi>ART.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:99817:94"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>When thou doſt greater Judgments <hi>SPARE,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And with thy knife but prune and <hi>PARE.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ev'n fruitful trees more fruitful <hi>ARE.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Such ſharpneſs ſhowes the ſweeteſt <hi>FREND:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Such cuttings rather heal then <hi>REND:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſuch beginnings touch their <hi>END.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Several ſins.</hi> F. Q.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Drunkenneſs.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It is a Thief, that oft before his face,</l>
                  <l>Steals man away, and layes a beaſt in's place.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Croſs ſin.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It is a ſhow'r, which e're we can get in,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And find a ſhelter,</hi> wets us to the ſkin.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sin of Infirmity.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is like the falling of an <hi>April</hi>-ſhow'r:</l>
                  <l>'Tis often rain, and ſun-ſhine in an hour.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sin of Custom,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is a long ſhow'r beginning withthe light;</l>
                  <l>Oft-times continuing till the dead of night.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sin of Ignorance,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It is a hideous miſt, that wets amain,</l>
                  <l>Though it appears not in the form of rain.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Crying ſin.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It is a ſudden ſhow'r that tears in ſunder,</l>
                  <l>The cope of Heaven, and alway comes with thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sin of Delight.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is like a feather'd ſhow'r of ſnow, not felt,</l>
                  <l>But ſoaks to th' very ſkin when e're it melt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sin of Preſumption,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Does like a ſhow'r of hail, both wet and wound</l>
                  <l>With ſudden death, or ſtrikes us to the ground.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The ſin of Sins.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It is a ſulph'rous ſhow'r, like that which fell.</l>
                  <l>On <hi>Sodom,</hi> ſtrikes, and ſtrikes to th' pit of Hell.</l>
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:99817:95"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lord, let thy ſaving Grace thy ſervants ſhrow'd,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Till we arrive where's neither ſhow'r nor cloud.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Repentance.</hi> F. Q.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis not to cry God mercy, or to ſit</l>
                  <l>And droop; or to confeſs that thou haſt fail'd:</l>
                  <l>'Tis to bewail the ſins thou didſt commit,</l>
                  <l>And not commit thoſe ſins thou haſt bewail'd.</l>
                  <l>He that bewails, and not forſakes them too,</l>
                  <l>Confeſſes rather what he means to do.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Praiſe.</hi> G. H.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>King of Glory, King of Peace!</l>
                  <l>I will love thee:</l>
                  <l>And that love may never ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>I will move thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou haſt granted my requeſt,</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt heard me:</l>
                  <l>Thou did'ſt note my working breaſt;</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt ſpar'd me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Therefore with my utmoſt art,</l>
                  <l>I will ſing thee:</l>
                  <l>And the cream of all my heart</l>
                  <l>I will bring thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though my ſins againſt me cry'd,</l>
                  <l>Thou didſt clear me:</l>
                  <l>And alone, when they reply'd,</l>
                  <l>Thou didſt hear me.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The Offering.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Since my ſadneſs</l>
                  <l>Into Gladneſs</l>
                  <l>Lord thou doſt convert,</l>
                  <l>O accept</l>
                  <l>What thou haſt kept</l>
                  <l>As thy due deſert.</l>
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:99817:95"/>
                  <l>Had I many,</l>
                  <l>Had I my,</l>
                  <l>(For this heart is none)</l>
                  <l>All were thine,</l>
                  <l>And none of mine,</l>
                  <l>Surely thine alone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet thy favour</l>
                  <l>May give ſavour</l>
                  <l>To this poor Oblation;</l>
                  <l>And it raiſe</l>
                  <l>To be thy praiſe,</l>
                  <l>And be my Salvation.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Light.</hi> A. C.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hail active nature's watchful life and health!</l>
                  <l>Her joy, her ornament and wealth!</l>
                  <l>Hail to thy Husband heat, and thee!</l>
                  <l>Thou the world's beauteous Bride, the luſtry Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom he.</l>
                  <l>Say from what Golden quivers of the Sky,</l>
                  <l>Do all thy winged arrows fly?</l>
                  <l>Swiftneſs and Power by Birth are thine:</l>
                  <l>From thy great Sire they came, thy Sire the word Divine.</l>
                  <l>'Tis I believe, thine archery to ſhow,</l>
                  <l>That ſo much coſt in colours thou,</l>
                  <l>And ſkill in painting doſt beſtow</l>
                  <l>Upon thine antient arms, the gaudy Heavenly bow.</l>
                  <l>Swift as wing'd thoughts their light carrier do run</l>
                  <l>Thy race is finiſht when begun:</l>
                  <l>Let a Poſt-Angel ſtart with thee,</l>
                  <l>And thou the Goal of earth ſhalt reach as ſoon as he,</l>
                  <l>Thou in the Moons bright chariot proud and gay,</l>
                  <l>Doſt thy bright world of Stars ſurvey;</l>
                  <l>And all the year doth with thee bring</l>
                  <l>A thouſand flowry lights, thine own Nocturnal ſpring</l>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:99817:96"/>
                  <l>Thou <hi>Scythian</hi> like doſt round thy lands above</l>
                  <l>The Suns gilt tent for ever move;</l>
                  <l>And ſtill as thou in pomp doſt go,</l>
                  <l>The ſhining Pageants of the world attend thy ſhow.</l>
                  <l>Nor amidſt all theſe triumphs doſt thou ſcorn</l>
                  <l>The humble glow-worms to adorn,</l>
                  <l>And with thoſe living ſpangles gild</l>
                  <l>(O greatneſs without pride) the buſhes of the field.</l>
                  <l>Night, and her ugly ſubjects thou doſt fright;</l>
                  <l>And ſleep, the lazy Owl of night:</l>
                  <l>Aſham'd, and fearful to appear</l>
                  <l>They ſkreen their horrid ſhapes with the black He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſphere.</l>
                  <l>At thy appearance fear it ſelf growes bold;</l>
                  <l>Thy ſun-ſhine melts away his cold:</l>
                  <l>Enconrag'd at the ſight of thee,</l>
                  <l>To the Cheek colour comes, and firmneſs to the Knee.</l>
                  <l>Ev'n luſt, the maſter of a harden'd face,</l>
                  <l>Bluſhes, if thou be'ſt in the place;</l>
                  <l>To darkneſs Curtains he retires,</l>
                  <l>In ſympathiſing night he rowls his ſmoaky fires.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Queen of Beauties,</hi> thou liſt'ſt up thy head,</l>
                  <l>Out of the Mornings purple bed,</l>
                  <l>The quire of birds about thee play,</l>
                  <l>And all the joyful world ſalutes the riſing day.</l>
                  <l>All the worlds brav'ry that delights our eyes,</l>
                  <l>Is but thy ſeveral liveries;</l>
                  <l>Thou the rich dye on them beſtow'ſt,</l>
                  <l>Thy nimble pencil paints this landſhape as thou go'ſt.</l>
                  <l>A crimſon garment in the roſe thou wear'ſt:</l>
                  <l>A Crown of ſtudded Gold thou bear'ſt;</l>
                  <l>The Virgin-lillies in their white,</l>
                  <l>Are clad but with the lawn of almoſt naked light.</l>
                  <l>The Violet like a little Infant ſtands,</l>
                  <l>Girt in thy purple ſwadling bands:</l>
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:99817:96"/>
                  <l>On the fair Tulip thou doſt dote:</l>
                  <l>Thou cloth'ſt it in a gay, and party colour'd coat.</l>
                  <l>But when firm bodies thy free courſe oppoſe,</l>
                  <l>Gently thy ſource the Land o're flows;</l>
                  <l>Takes there poſſeſſion, and does make</l>
                  <l>Of colours mingled, light, a thick and ſtanding lake.</l>
                  <l>But the vaſt Ocean of unbounded day,</l>
                  <l>In th' Empyraean Heaven does ſtay:</l>
                  <l>Thy Rivers, Lakes and Springs below</l>
                  <l>From thence took firſt their riſe, thither at laſt muſt flow.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Succeſs.</hi> G. S. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Unleſs the Lord the houſe ſuſtain,</l>
                  <l>They build in vain,</l>
                  <l>In vain they watch unleſs the Lord,</l>
                  <l>The City Guard.</l>
                  <l>In vain ye riſe before the light,</l>
                  <l>And break the ſlumbers of the night:</l>
                  <l>In vain the bread of ſorrows eat,</l>
                  <l>Got by your ſweat;</l>
                  <l>Unleſs the Lord with good ſucceſs</l>
                  <l>Your labours bleſs:</l>
                  <l>For he all good on his beſtows.</l>
                  <l>And crowns their eyes with ſweet repoſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Hope.</hi> A. C.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hope of all ills that men endure,</l>
                  <l>The only cheap and univerſal cure!</l>
                  <l>Thou captives freedom, and thou ſick mans health!</l>
                  <l>Thou looſers vict'ry, and thou beggars wealth!</l>
                  <l>Thou Manna, which from Heav'n we eat,</l>
                  <l>To ev'ry taſt a ſeveral Meat!</l>
                  <l>Thou ſtrong retreat! thou ſure intail'd Eſtate,</l>
                  <l>Which nought has power to alienate!</l>
                  <l>Thou pleaſant, honeſt flatterer! For none</l>
                  <l>Flatter unhappy men but thou alone.</l>
                  <pb n="164" facs="tcp:99817:97"/>
                  <l>Hope, thou firſt fruits of happineſs!</l>
                  <l>Thou gentle dawning of a bright ſucceſs!</l>
                  <l>Thou good preparative, without which our joy</l>
                  <l>Does work too ſtrong and whilſt it cures deſtroy;</l>
                  <l>Who out of tortures reach doſt ſtand,</l>
                  <l>And art a Bleſſing ſtill in hand!</l>
                  <l>Whilſt thee, her <hi>Earneſt-money</hi> we retain,</l>
                  <l>We certain are to gain,</l>
                  <l>Whether ſhe her bargain break, or elſe fulfil,</l>
                  <l>Thou only good, not worſe for ending ill.</l>
                  <l>Brother of Faith, 'twixt whom and thee</l>
                  <l>The joyes of Heaven and Earth divided be!</l>
                  <l>Though faith be Heir, and have the firſt Eſtate,</l>
                  <l>Thy portion yet in moveables is great.</l>
                  <l>Happineſs it ſelf's all one</l>
                  <l>In thee, or in Poſſeſſion:</l>
                  <l>Only the future's thine, and preſent his:</l>
                  <l>Thine's the more hard and noble bliſs.</l>
                  <l>Beſt Apprehender of our joyes which haſt</l>
                  <l>So long a reach, and yet canſt hold ſo faſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Good Conſcience.</hi> Q.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>A Conſcience pure, unſtain'd by ſin,</l>
                  <l>Is Braſs without, and Gold within.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Holy Heart.</hi> F. Q.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Royal Off-ſpring of a ſecond Birth,</l>
                  <l>Sets ope to Heaven, and ſhuts the doors to Earth.</l>
                  <l>If Earth (Heavens Rival) dart her idle Ray,</l>
                  <l>To Heaven 'tis wax, and to the world 'tis Clay.</l>
                  <l>If earth preſent delights, it ſcorns to draw;</l>
                  <l>But, like the Jet unrubb'd, diſdains that ſtraw.</l>
                  <l>No hope deceives it, and no doubt divides it;</l>
                  <l>No grief diſturbs it, and no errour guides it.</l>
                  <l>No fear diſtracts it, and no rage inflames it;</l>
                  <l>No guilt condemns it, and no folly ſhames it.</l>
                  <l>No ſloth beſots it, and no luſt inthrals it;</l>
                  <l>No ſcorn afflicts it, and no paſſion galls it.</l>
                  <pb n="165" facs="tcp:99817:97"/>
                  <l>It is a Carknet of immortal Life;</l>
                  <l>An Ark of Peace; the liſts of ſacred ſtriſe;</l>
                  <l>A purer piece of endleſs tranſitory;</l>
                  <l>A ſhrine of Grace, a little Throne of Glory.</l>
                  <l>A Heaven born Off-ſpring of a new born Birth;</l>
                  <l>An earthly Heaven, an ounce of Heavenly earth.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Man's Life.</hi> F. Q.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our life is nothing but a winters day:</l>
                  <l>Some only break their faſt, and ſo away:</l>
                  <l>Others ſtay dinner, and depart full ſed;</l>
                  <l>The deepeſt age but ſups, and goes to bed.</l>
                  <l>He's moſt in debt that lingers out the day:</l>
                  <l>Who dies betime has leſs, and leſs to pay.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Man's Folly.</hi> I. C.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lord, what a fooliſh thing is man!</l>
                  <l>How fond is he of toyes!</l>
                  <l>How does he ſpend that little ſpan</l>
                  <l>Of his in empty joyes!</l>
                  <l>But for that precious ſoul of his,</l>
                  <l>He takes no further care</l>
                  <l>To fit it for immortal bliſs</l>
                  <l>Such thoughts too ſerious are.</l>
                  <l>Himſelf to every pleaſure gives,</l>
                  <l>And drowns his ſoul in luſt:</l>
                  <l>In all deſtructive ſins he lives;</l>
                  <l>'Till levell'd with the duſt.</l>
                  <l>Give me, O Lord, that pious care,</l>
                  <l>And that obſequious love;</l>
                  <l>That all my actions may declare,</l>
                  <l>I ſeek that place above.</l>
                  <l>Where we from ſin exempt ſhall be;</l>
                  <l>From ſorrow and from tears:</l>
                  <l>And where no trouble we ſhall ſee,</l>
                  <l>Nor be diſturb'd with ſears.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:99817:98"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chriſt Crucified.</hi> R. F.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Behold and ſee, if ever any pain</l>
                  <l>Did match his ſorrow who for us was ſlain!</l>
                  <l>Lo, God bleeds on the Croſs! high Heav'n deſcends</l>
                  <l>In blood to make man and his Maker friends.</l>
                  <l>When guilty man lay doom'd Eternally</l>
                  <l>To Death and Hell, ev'n God himſelf could dye,</l>
                  <l>And ſmile upon thoſe wounds, that ſpear, that grave,</l>
                  <l>Which our Rebellion merited and gave.</l>
                  <l>This love exceeds all height: yet I confeſs</l>
                  <l>'Twas God that did it, how could it be leſs?</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Death.</hi> J. D.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Death, be nor proud, though ſome have called thee</l>
                  <l>Mighty and dreadful: for thou art not ſo.</l>
                  <l>For thoſe, whom thou think'ſt thou doſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw,</l>
                  <l>Die not, poor death; nor yet canſt thou kill me.</l>
                  <l>From reſt and ſleep, which but thy picture be,</l>
                  <l>Much pleaſure, then from thee much more muſt flow:</l>
                  <l>And ſooneſt our beſt men with thee do go,</l>
                  <l>Reſt of their bones, and ſouls delivery;</l>
                  <l>Th' art ſlave to fate, chance, Kings and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate men;</l>
                  <l>And doſt with poyſon, war and ſickneſs dwell:</l>
                  <l>Hard pains or poppy make us ſleep as well,</l>
                  <l>And better then thy ſtroke: why ſwell'ſt thou then</l>
                  <l>One ſhort ſleep paſt, we wake Eternally;</l>
                  <l>And death ſhall be no more, death, thou ſhalt dye.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Reſurrection.</hi> I. D.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>At the round earth's imagin'd corners blow</l>
                  <l>Your trumpets, Angels: men ariſe, ariſe</l>
                  <l>From death; you numberleſs infinities</l>
                  <l>Of ſouls unto your ſcatter'd bodies go;</l>
                  <l>All whom one floud did, and fire ſhall or'ethrow;</l>
                  <l>All whom war, death, age, agues, tyrannies,</l>
                  <l>Deſpair, law, chance hath ſlain, and you whoſe eyes</l>
                  <l>Shall behold God, and never taſt death's wo.</l>
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:99817:98"/>
                  <l>But let them ſleep, Lord, and me mourn a ſpace,</l>
                  <l>For if above all theſe my ſins abound,</l>
                  <l>'Tis late to ask abundance of thy Grace,</l>
                  <l>When we are there. Here on this lowly ground</l>
                  <l>Teach me how to repent: for that's as good</l>
                  <l>As if th' 'adſt ſeal'd my pardon with thy blood.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Judgment-Day.</hi> R. C.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hear'ſt thou my Soul, what ſerious things,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Prophets ſay,</hi> the Pſalmiſt ſings</l>
                  <l>Of a ſtrict Judge from whoſe ſharp ray,</l>
                  <l>The world in flames ſhall fly away.</l>
                  <l>O that fire! before whoſe face</l>
                  <l>Heav'n and Earth ſhall find no place.</l>
                  <l>O thoſe eyes! whoſe angry light</l>
                  <l>Muſt be the day of that dread night.</l>
                  <l>O that trump! whoſe blaſt ſhall run,</l>
                  <l>An even round with th' circling ſun,</l>
                  <l>And urge the murm'ring graves to bring</l>
                  <l>Pale Mankind forth to meet their King.</l>
                  <l>Horrour of nature, Hell and Death!</l>
                  <l>When a deep groan ſhall from beneath</l>
                  <l>Cry out, <hi>We come, we come;</hi> and all</l>
                  <l>The caves of night anſwer one call.</l>
                  <l>O that book! whoſe leaves ſo bright</l>
                  <l>Will ſet the world in ſevere light:</l>
                  <l>O the Judge! whoſe Hand, whoſe Eye,</l>
                  <l>None can endure, yet none can fly.</l>
                  <l>Yet thou giv'ſt leave, dread Lord, that we</l>
                  <l>Take ſhelter from thy ſelf in thee;</l>
                  <l>And with the wings of thine own Dove</l>
                  <l>Fly to thy Sceptre of ſoft love.</l>
                  <l>Mercy, my Judge, mercy I cry,</l>
                  <l>With bluſhing cheek, and bleeding eye:</l>
                  <l>The conſcious colours of my ſin</l>
                  <l>Are red without, and pale within.</l>
                  <pb n="168" facs="tcp:99817:99"/>
                  <l>O let thine own ſoft bowels pay</l>
                  <l>Thy ſelf, and ſo diſcharge that day.</l>
                  <l>If ſin can ſigh, love can forgive:</l>
                  <l>O ſay the word, my ſoul ſhall live.</l>
                  <l>O when thy laſt frown ſhall proclaim</l>
                  <l>The flocks of goats to folds of flame;</l>
                  <l>And all thy loſt ſheep found ſhall be,</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>come ye bleſſed</hi> then call me.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Heaven.</hi> G. F.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Behold this houſe where man doth now reſide.</l>
                  <l>The flow'rs pour out their odours in his way:</l>
                  <l>To ſerve him all the creatures take a pride:</l>
                  <l>The winds do ſweep his chambers ev'ry day,</l>
                  <l>And clouds do waſh his rooms: the ceiling gay</l>
                  <l>Starred aloſt the gilded knobs imbrave.</l>
                  <l>If ſuch a houſe God to another gave,</l>
                  <l>How ſhine thoſe glitt'ring Courts he for himſelf will have?</l>
                  <l>And if a ſullen cloud, as ſad as night,</l>
                  <l>In which the Sun may ſeem imbodied,</l>
                  <l>Depur'd of all his droſs we ſee ſo white,</l>
                  <l>Burning in melted Gold his watry head.</l>
                  <l>Or round with Ivory edges ſilvered,</l>
                  <l>What Luſtre ſuper-excellent will he</l>
                  <l>Lighten on thoſe that ſhall his ſun-ſhine ſee,</l>
                  <l>In that all glorious Court, in which all glories be.</l>
                  <l>If but one Sun with his diffuſive fires,</l>
                  <l>Can paint the Stars, and the whole world with light;</l>
                  <l>And joy and life into each heart inſpires;</l>
                  <l>And ev'ry Saint ſhall ſhine in Heaven as bright</l>
                  <l>As doth the Sun in his tranſcendent might,</l>
                  <l>(As ſaith may well believe what truth once ſayes)</l>
                  <l>What ſhall ſo many Suns united Rayes</l>
                  <l>But dazle all the eyes, that now in Heav'n we praiſe?</l>
                  <l>Here that bright band, that now in triumph ſhines,</l>
                  <l>And that (before they were inveſted thus)</l>
                  <pb n="169" facs="tcp:99817:99"/>
                  <l>In earthly bodies carried Heavenly minds,</l>
                  <l>Pitch, round about a Throne moſt glorious,</l>
                  <l>Their ſunny tents, and houſes luminous;</l>
                  <l>All their Eternal day in Songs employing,</l>
                  <l>Joying their end, without end of their joying,</l>
                  <l>While their Almighty Prince, deſtruction is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying.</l>
                  <l>Full, but yet never cloy'd with what might whet</l>
                  <l>And dull the keeneſt craving Appetite:</l>
                  <l>Where never Sun did riſe, nor ever ſet;</l>
                  <l>But one Eternal day, and endleſs light</l>
                  <l>Gives time to thoſe, whoſe time is infinite:</l>
                  <l>Speaking with thought, obtaining without ſee;</l>
                  <l>Beholding him whom never eye could ſee,</l>
                  <l>And magnifying him, that cannot greater be:</l>
                  <l>How can ſuch joy as this want words to ſpeak?</l>
                  <l>And yet what words can ſpeak ſuch joy as this?</l>
                  <l>Far from the world that might their quiet break,</l>
                  <l>Here the glad ſouls the face of beauty kiſs,</l>
                  <l>Pour'd out in pleaſure on their beds of bliſs:</l>
                  <l>And drunk with Nectar-Torrents, ever hold</l>
                  <l>Their eyes on him, whoſe Graces manifold,</l>
                  <l>The more they do behold, the more they would behold.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Happineſs.</hi> F. Q.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I love, and have ſome cauſe to love the earth:</l>
                  <l>She is my Makers creature; therefore good:</l>
                  <l>She is my Mother; for ſhe gave me birth:</l>
                  <l>She is my tender Nurſe; ſhe gives me food.</l>
                  <l>But what's a creature, Lord, compar'd with thee?</l>
                  <l>Or what's my Mother, or my Nurſe to me?</l>
                  <l>I love the Air; her dainty ſweets refreſh</l>
                  <l>My drooping ſoul, and to new ſweets invite me:</l>
                  <l>Her ſhrill-mouth'd quire ſuſtain me with their fleſh,</l>
                  <l>And with their <hi>Polyphonian</hi> notes delight me.</l>
                  <l>But what's the air, or all the ſweets that ſhe</l>
                  <l>Can bleſs my Soul withal, compar'd to thee?</l>
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:99817:100" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>I love the Sea; ſhe is my fellow-creature,</l>
                  <l>My careful Purveyor; ſhe provides me ſtore;</l>
                  <l>She walls me round; ſhe makes my diet greater;</l>
                  <l>She waſts my treaſure from a forreign ſhore.</l>
                  <l>But Lord of Oceans, when compar'd with thee,</l>
                  <l>What is the Ocean, or her wealth to me?</l>
                  <l>To Heaven's high City I direct my Journey,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſpangled Suburbs entertain mine eye;</l>
                  <l>Mine eye, by contemplations great attorney,</l>
                  <l>Tranſcends the Cryſtal pavement of the Sky.</l>
                  <l>But what is Heav'n great God, compar'd to thee?</l>
                  <l>Without thy preſence Heav'n's no Heaven to me.</l>
                  <l>Without thy preſence earth gives no refection;</l>
                  <l>Without thy preſence ſea affords no treaſure;</l>
                  <l>Without thy preſence air's a rank infection;</l>
                  <l>Without thy preſence Heav'n it ſelf's no pleaſure.</l>
                  <l>If nor poſſeſt, if not enjoy'd in thee,</l>
                  <l>What's earth, or ſea, or air, or Heav'n to me?</l>
                  <l>The higheſt honours that the world can boaſt,</l>
                  <l>Are Subjects far too low for my deſire:.</l>
                  <l>The brighteſt beams of Glory are (at moſt)</l>
                  <l>But dying ſparkles of thy living fire.</l>
                  <l>The proudeſt flames that earth can kindle, be</l>
                  <l>But nightly Glow-worms, if compar'd to thee.</l>
                  <l>Without thy preſence, wealth are bags of cares;</l>
                  <l>Wiſdom, but folly; joy, diſquiet ſadneſs:</l>
                  <l>Friendſhip is treaſon, and delights are ſnares;</l>
                  <l>Pleaſures but pain, and mirth, but pleaſant mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</l>
                  <l>Without thee, Lord, things be not what they be;</l>
                  <l>Nor have they being when compar'd with thee.</l>
                  <l>In having all things, and not thee, what have I?</l>
                  <l>Not having thee, what have my labours got?</l>
                  <l>Let me enjoy but thee, what farther crave I?</l>
                  <l>And having thee alone, what have I not?</l>
                  <l>I wiſh nor Sea, nor Land, nor would I be</l>
                  <l>Poſſeſt of Heav'n, Heav'n unpoſſeſt of thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:99817:100"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
